<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The adventures of (Mr. T.S.) an English merchant taken prisoner by the Turks of Argiers, and carried into the inland countries of Africa : with a description of the kingdom of Argiers ... / written first by the author, and fitted for the public view by A. Roberts ; whereunto is annex'd an observation of the tide, and how to turn a ship out of the straights mouth, the wind being westerly, by Richard Norris.</title>
            <author>T. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 134 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16016349</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16016349</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The adventures of (Mr. T.S.) an English merchant taken prisoner by the Turks of Argiers, and carried into the inland countries of Africa : with a description of the kingdom of Argiers ... / written first by the author, and fitted for the public view by A. Roberts ; whereunto is annex'd an observation of the tide, and how to turn a ship out of the straights mouth, the wind being westerly, by Richard Norris.</title>
                  <author>T. S.</author>
                  <author>Roberts, A., 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Norris, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 252, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Slavery --  Africa, North.</term>
               <term>Adventure and adventurers --  England.</term>
               <term>Algeria --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104773:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104773:1"/>
            <p>THE ADVENTURES OF (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>T. S.</hi>) AN ENGLISH MERCHANT, Taken Priſoner by the <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKS</hi> of <hi>ARGIERS,</hi> And carried into the INLAND COUNTRIES OF AFRICA: With a Deſcription of the Kingdom of of
<hi>ARGIERS,</hi> of all the TOWNS and PLACES of Note thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added a Relation of the Chief Commodities of the Countrey, and of the Actions and Manners of the People.</p>
            <p>Written firſt by the Author, and fitted for the Publick view by
<hi>A. Roberts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is annex'd an Obſervation of the Tide, and how to turn a Ship out of the <hi>Straights Mouth</hi> the Wind being Weſterly; By
<hi>Richard Norris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi> at the <hi>White Hart</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104773:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104773:2"/>
            <head>To his very worthy Friend THOMAS MANLEY ESQUIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I ſend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the <hi>Memoires</hi> of our Deceaſed Friend, that you have oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſired to peruſe; I hope you will meet in
<pb facs="tcp:104773:3"/> them with that ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that you do expect; for they contain many uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Obſervations, adorned with variety of most pleaſant
<hi>ADVENTURES:</hi> They may appear very ſtrange to ſuch as have ſeen nothing but their Cradle; with them they may obtain the Credit of a well humoured <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance:</hi> But <hi>Sir,</hi> You are ſufficiently acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the integrity of <pb facs="tcp:104773:3"/> the <hi>AUTHOR,</hi> to cauſe you to put a higher value upon this Relation; and I know that you are ſo well informed of the Proceedings of the <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> People, that you will not find in it ſuch incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Wonders as preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced perſons may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. Two or three Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages look like Miracles, but they may be confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſeveral of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both Merchants and <pb facs="tcp:104773:4"/> Travellers, that have ſeen in thoſe parts the things related; from them any may be further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. The Author was not willing to let the world know ſo much of his Life, had he not been ſollicited and almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it by the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe whoſe Request he did not dare to deny. Death hath carried him another Voyage while he was writing this, and <pb facs="tcp:104773:4"/> forced him to leave his Work unperfect in my hands; could he but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, I doubt not but we might have another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from him as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as this, and no leſs wonderful.</p>
            <p>This Age in which we live is apt to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit what it underſtands not, or ſees not acted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its Eyes; but its Malice or Cenſures will never injure the Author; <pb facs="tcp:104773:5"/> he is ſafe out of the Reach of Envy: So may this his Relation be in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of ſo powerful and kind a Patron. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful Servant, A. ROBERTS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104773:5"/>
            <head>The Adventures of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant taken Captive by the <hi>Turks</hi> of <hi>Argiers,</hi> and carried about the In-land Countries of <hi>Africa,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent Obſervations both curious and profitable.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance of the World, and in the diſpoſition of Mankind; it carries us through various Eſtates, it brings us in Dangers and Miſeries, and in a due time leads us out again by means <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104773:6"/> not diſcoverable to our ſhallow foreſight; it cauſeth us to meet with ſuch different Accidents, which ſome may attribute to Chance; but if we take the pains to examine and queſtion them, we ſhall find them to be appointed by a Divine Wiſdom for the Publick and our own Advantage:
<hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> is a Famous Inſtance; He was ſold by his Brethren, he paſt through <hi>Potiphera</hi>'s Houſe to the Common Gaol, and from the next door to the Gallows, he was promoted to
<hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Elbow, to preſerve that Kingdom from the Fury of ſeven years Famine. Some it raiſes from a Cottage to a Throne; it tumbles others down to the moſt deſpicable condition: We may ſee a
<hi>Belliſarius</hi> the moſt ſucceſſeful Warrior of his time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to beg his Bread in that City that he had reſcued from the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104773:6"/> Enemies hands; A proud <hi>Bajazet</hi> who makes the World bow to his Scepter, ſerves many times for a Footſtool to his Enemy. Modern and Ancient Hiſtories are full of ſuch ſtrange Examples of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of Providence, which tend many times only to faſhion and frame us to a certain temper that may make us more uſeful in our Generations.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not engage my ſelf to ſhew all the Intrigues, all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſecret Actings of Gods Providence, that is the buſineſs of a Divine, and not of one whoſe Profeſſion is to Trade.</p>
            <p>Some of my Friends have ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired me to give the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick an Account of ſome Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that I have made in my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels into the In-land Country of <hi>Affrica,</hi> where my Misfortune carried me; I hope that ſome may <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104773:7"/> make no ſmall Advantage of them.</p>
            <p>My Name will be uſeleſs to the Judicious Reader; I will only tell him, That I was firſt deſigned for a Scholar; but an old Pedant ſoon frighted me from my Studies by his extraordinary Rigour; he gave me ſuch an averſion for Learning, which formerly I eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I could not endure the ſight of a Book.</p>
            <p>My Eſtate being that of a youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother, and but very ſmall, I was perſwaded next to embrace the employment of a Merchant; therefore I was bound an Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to a noted Trader in <hi>London.</hi> After five years abode in his houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he reſolved to ſend me as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and other Places within the <hi>Straights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At that time, in the Year 1648<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my Father dies, and my Elder
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104773:7"/> Brother was kill'd in our unhappy Troubles. They left me an Eſtate which might have obliged me to reſide at home, had not the deſire of ſeeing Foreign Places, and the vain-glory of being named a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller, with my Maſters Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, forced me abroad, and to continue in my former Deſign. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my departure, I ſold ſome of my Eſtate, and bought a
<hi>Cargo</hi> of Goods to the value of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand odd hundred Pounds.</p>
            <p>With this and ſome Goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to my Maſter, I embark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the latter end of <hi>July</hi> in a Veſſel of <hi>Hamborough</hi> of 350 Tuns, called the <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> whereof <hi>Peter Janſon</hi> was Maſter, in the River of <hi>Thames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Wind favoured us very much out of the Channel, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we met with contrary Guſts, in 20 days we reach'd as <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104773:8"/> far as the Cape St. <hi>Vincent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Buſineſs made us direct our Courſe towards
<hi>Cadiz,</hi> where we had ſome Goods to unload.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as we came near the Cape, we ſaw two Ships to Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, making all Sail to come up with us; we began to be jealous of their Intentions, and to prepare for our Defence. The Decks were cleared, the Guns charged, and every one had his Place and Office appointed him; we were all between hope and fear, as in ſuch Caſes is uſual, until their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours had ſatisfied us. Many idle Conjectures did ſpread amongſt us; ſome imagined them to be <hi>French</hi> by the make of their Ships, others that they were <hi>Turks;</hi> one wiſer than the reſt, knew them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off, and affirm'd them to be <hi>Oſtenders,</hi> the ſame in which he had formerly ſailed, naming the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104773:8"/> one the St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> the other the <hi>Capitain.</hi> Our diſtruſt made us ſeek the ſhelter of the Land, until at laſt we ſaw <hi>French</hi> Colours out, and heard a Gun that commanded us to ſtrike Sail. Some of our Company well acquainted with ſuch Tricks of Pirates, adviſed our giddy headed Skipper not to truſt their Appearance, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill his Courſe. But his ill Fortune and ours would not ſuffer him to follow ſuch wholſom Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which might have put him and us out of all danger. For although it was the Morning when the Chaſe began, and that the Enemy had won much upon us that day, they could never have come up to us until Evening; and in the Night we might have made our Eſcape, and got into the Harbour. But he had a Deſign which we never could well underſtand. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104773:9"/> he commanded to lay by the Wind, until the Ships came within Call. They came too ſoon for us; at half a League diſtance they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered themſelves to be <hi>Turks</hi> Men of War by their bloody Colours, which they put out inſtead of the White: Then began our Skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be amazed, our Company to be frighted, and every one to beſtir himſelf. I obſerved a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low who before had ſome Diſeaſe in his Legs and hands much like unto the Gout, which made him unprofitable all the time of the Voyage, when he ſaw the danger, he began to skip about, and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Guns as if nothing had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ailed him. We had then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board about a hundred Men with the Paſſengers of ſeveral Nations, and thirty great Pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with other ſmaller Guns. It had been an unworthy Act to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104773:9"/> our ſelves into the Enemies hands without a ſtroke, being ſo well provided for our Defence.</p>
            <p>About ſeven of the Clock in the Afternoon the <hi>Turks</hi> overtook us, and the formoſt Veſſel gave us a Broad Side, the other followed, and ſaluted us in the ſame manner. We ſtood not ſtill in the mean while, but returned them the like. The Fight was furious and bloody on both ſides for four hours: Our men hehaved themſelves gallantly; neither Death nor Wounds could force them from their Charge and Poſts. Some when their Limbs were all bruiſed, their Bones ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and their Bodies torn with Splinters, did obſtinately continue to handle and manage the Guns. Every one reſolved to die with his Weapons in his hand, rather than to ſhrink in the leaſt from the Fight.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104773:10"/>In the ſpace of four hours we received near fifty Broad ſides, and our Enemies were as obſtinate as our ſelves.</p>
            <p>At laſt our Number was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to 18 men, and thoſe were wounded in ſeveral places, the reſt were either dead or diſabled. The Skipper was ſhot through the Thigh, my ſelf through the right Arm; ſo that we could no longer reſiſt the Numbers and Fury of our Enemies, that continued ſtill to poure upon us great and ſmall Shot: Beſides we had another Misfortune that happened unto us happily as it fell out; our Ship was wounded with a great Shot between Wind and Water, ſo that being in ſuch a craſie Veſſel, and with ſuch craſie Bodies, we made but a faint reſiſtance, which the <hi>Turks</hi> perceiving, and fearing that the Sea would at laſt ſwallow us, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104773:10"/> and deprive them of their Booty, they reſolved to venture to board us: On both ſides they grappled with us, and entered their men, which we from our Fore-Caſtle and Steerage did force aboard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with our Murdering Pieces; at laſt, for fear our Obſtinacy would cauſe our Ship to ſink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us, and deliver us into the hands of a more mercileſs Enemy, the raging Sea; we called for Quarter, which the <hi>Turks</hi> were glad to grant, having almoſt loſt all Courage and hopes of forcing us to a Surrender; therefore they willingly accepted of the firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: We found that near 300 of their men had been killed, and their Ships were miſerably torn and maimed. One thing paſſed during the Fight worthy our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and which I did then look upon as an ill Omen; at a Broad
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104773:11"/> Side one great Shot was forced back again, and ſplit in pieces; we did conceive that it had met with a more violent one, which had driven it upon us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> treated us very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly, that we expected not from Enemies which we had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by ſo long a Reſiſtance. They commended our Courage, and wondered at our Reſolution. And when they ſaw the rich Loading that they had got into their hands, they quickly pardoned us the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries we had done them.</p>
            <p>The Captains and Owners of the <hi>Turks</hi> Ships called me &amp; our Skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to an Account for the Bills of Loading, which, when there was no remedy, we delivered into their hands.</p>
            <p>I made ſome Reflections upon my former Condition, and wiſhed my ſelf upon ſome Chriſtian ſhore <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104773:11"/> as poor as
<hi>Job;</hi> Liberty was ſweet to me that was taken a Slave: I remembred then that excellent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>Truſt not unto uncertain riches, &amp;c.</hi> I then condemned the joy I had felt for the rich Patrimony that was left me, and the earneſt deſire for to ſee Foreign Places. Now to my ſorrow I began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my former Condition; but all theſe Reflections and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets could not turn the Wind, nor ſtop our Courſe from
<hi>Argiers,</hi> where we were bound next; for when our Ship had been ſeized, we that were alive were diſpoſed of into the Enemies Ships, and ſtript of our beſt Attire, which ſome luſty Rogues did us the kindneſs to wear for our ſakes before our eyes.</p>
            <p>Our dead Bodies, and thoſe that were wounded deſperately, of whom there was ſmall hopes, <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104773:12"/> were ſtript naked, and ſent in that condition to feed the Sharkes and other Ravenous Fiſhes of the Sea; ſome we ſaw at that Inſtant wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us, as we did conceive, for that intent: It may be they were as ſenſible of dead Bodies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, as Vultures are, who conſtantly hover about a Houſe or Tent in theſe Countries, where the Sick are contained that will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly die, in hopes to enjoy the Prey when it is to be expoſed and carried out.</p>
            <p>During our ſtay a ſhipboard, we were as civilly treated as we could expect from <hi>Turks,</hi> and did feed as they did upon Garlick &amp; Rusk, poor <hi>John,</hi> Rice, &amp; ſuch like food. I obſerved them very inquiſitive to find out our Qualities, and the Eſtates that we had remaining, our Friends, and what Aſſiſtance and Favour we might expect from <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104773:12"/> them. To know theſe Particulars, we were examined apart: We had been forewarned of this Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore we had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Anſwers, that we might not be found in a contradiction. I had deſired our Company to make me paſs for a poor Fellow, whoſe Induſtry had obtained the Truſt of that conſiderable <hi>Cargo,</hi> which as we did give out did belong to my Maſter.</p>
            <p>This Anſwer ſatisfied them for a while, but meeting in the Ship with ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Renegadoes, by an inconſiderate Diſcourſe about ſeveral Particulars, one of them began to have ſome ſuſpition and knowledge of me, becauſe he had ſeen me at the unloading of ſome Goods by the Water ſide, and did remember that then more reſpect was paid to me than ſuch a poor Fellow could expect or claim. I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104773:13"/> laboured to excuſe my Raſhneſs, and to juſtifie my former Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nevertheleſs one word made me to be ſuſpected for an eminent Perſon, powerful in Friends and Acquaintance, which made them put a higher Value upon me, and hope for a greater Ranſom.</p>
            <p>We ſailed into the <hi>Streights,</hi> and at the Entry, over againſt <hi>Gibral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> we met with a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Man of War at ſome diſtance from us; he laboured to come to ſpeak with us, but the
<hi>Turks</hi> were not in a Poſture, nor able to anſwer him in his own Language ſo loud as he could ſpeak; for in the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Fight they had broken ſome of their Ribs, and weakned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; therefore they hoiſed up all their Sails, and made away as faſt as the Prize-Ship could ſail. She received ſome Chaſe Guns from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who had almoſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104773:13"/> retaken her, but the Evening drawing on, ſhe had the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſaving her ſelf in the dark night: And the better to hinder the <hi>Spaniard</hi> from further Purſuit, one of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſtaid behind, and reſolutely gave a few Broad Sides to his Enemy.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Prize got out of ſight, and the
<hi>Turks</hi> Veſſel followed with all ſpeed. The Night coming on apace, rid them of the importune company of the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day we anchored in the Bay of <hi>Algiers,</hi> where ſome Officers of the Town came to take notice of our Number, and of the Prize that was taken; one was a <hi>Corniſh</hi> man, that by his Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie had procured unto himſelf great Wealth amongſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> he was a Trader in Slaves, and knew well how to make his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104773:14"/> of his own Nation. He drew near us that were <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us in what part of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> we had been born; ſuch Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions being unpleaſing to us, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired as he was our Countreyman, that he would ſhew us ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and buy us for himſelf; we hoped to meet with a kinder En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment from one of the ſame Language and People: He told us that if we did give him hopes of returning his Money, he would venture to lay out ſome to do us a pleaſure, that we might not fall into ſevere hands that might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our Lives by a rough U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. He informed us, that if we came on ſhore, we ſhould be led to the Market, and there ſold as Horſes; That there are conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waiting ſome that knew how to find us out, that would treat us moſt inhumanely, and oblige us <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104773:14"/> to redeem our ſelves; That they would exact from us the remainder of our Eſtates to be at liberty; That we had beſt come into his hands; That he being our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyman, would endeavour to be our Friend, and take no more from us than it coſt him: Therefore he conjured us to diſcover our ſelves if we did love our own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and welfare, and to tell him what Encouragement he might have to lay out his Money for us, and what Security to have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. We began to look one upon another, to underſtand with our Eyes how inclinable each was to comply with his Deſire. We were ſomething jealous of the <hi>Turk</hi>'s Faith, and did believe that he that had not kept it to his God, would ſcarce be more careful to keep it with Men. We were long ſilent, and knew not what we <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104773:15"/> ſhould do in this caſe; but at laſt I ventured to deliver the Senſe of the Company, and to thank him in the name of four or five <hi>Engliſh</hi> that we were, for his kind Information, telling him that our Loſſes were great, that our Friends were many, that we had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet left at home able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us, were not too high a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue put upon us, and that we could give him ſufficient aſſurance that what I ſaid was true.</p>
            <p>At this Diſcovery all my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades began earneſtly to intreat him to ſhew ſome Favour to his Countreymen promiſing to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quite his Kindneſs with double in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p>Unto all our Offers the Deceit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful <hi>Turk</hi> began to liſten diligently for we afterwards ſaw that he in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended only to make a Prey of us and get ſuch Information from u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104773:15"/> as might ſerve his turn. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſuſpect him, and be ſorry for our credulity, when we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him in the company of the Owners of the Ship, offering for the moſt conſiderable of us large Sums of Money, leaving the reſt to their ill fortune, without the leaſt regard: They could not then agree about the Price, ſo that we were tranſported aſhore. At our firſt Landing, great Companies flock'd about us to ſee us, having been fore-informed that we had behaved our ſelves like men of Courage in the Fight. Some whoſe Relations had been killed, gave us ſuch Welcome as became the cruelty and impertinency of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: They loaded us with Curſes and Imprecations, and did ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſult over us. Had not our Guardians protected us from their Violence, I think we had been torn
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104773:16"/> in pieces. One amongſt the reſt was animated with a ſtrange fury and deſire of revenge for the death of his dear Comrade; both were <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Renegadoes: He drew his Cymeter at us, and begg'd the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſacrifice one of us, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to pay his Ranſome: When that could not be obtained, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired only to cut off our Ears. I know not how it happened that he came near one of us, and with a Blow ſtruck off part of the Cheek of a <hi>German,</hi> which he took and greedily ſwallowed, telling the Aſſiſtants that he never taſted ſo ſweet a Morſel in his days as that was; ſo ſtrangely Vengeance had transported him, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to feed upon us. It was our happineſs that our Lives did not depend upon his pleaſure, we had then accompanied his Comrade in the other world; but our Keepers <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104773:16"/> did ſafely convey us into the City, where we found our Chains ready made that waited for us. Every one of us had a great ſtrong Chain about twenty pound weight link'd to our Legs and tyed to our Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that if we did meditate an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, it might not be without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
            <p>We were conducted next in this ſtrange equipage with our jingling Chains at our ſides to the Kings Palace; we did not a little wonder what they intended to do with us in a place of ſo much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. We paſt the firſt Guard, and entred into a large and ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Court paved with white Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Stone, of which there is a great quantity in that Country; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the <hi>Quarries about old Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> or <hi>Tunis.</hi> There was a high Brick Wall that incloſed us, and before us opened a large Gate <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104773:17"/> Chequer'd with divers Colours, which led into a great Hall, where our Keepers led us, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to reſt our ſelves until the King of <hi>Argiers</hi> did give us a Viſit; an honour that we expected not; but it ſeems it is the Cuſtom that all Slaves ſhould come in his ſight when they firſt Land; for out of them he chuſes for himſelf the Tenth Perſon; and when that Number is not compleat, he never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs takes one whom he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>We were placed round about the Hall to be prepared for his Coming in, which was not ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for being about Noon, he had been bathing himſelf, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards taking another Recreation, which is uſual at that time of day in the hot Climates.</p>
            <p>About Two of the Clock in comes a luſty Officer clothed in Scarlet, with a Rod in his hand, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104773:17"/> and a great Turbant about his Head; it ſeems he was the King's Gentleman Uſher: He was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by ſix Perſons of good Meen and Appearance: They were armed with Cymeters.</p>
            <p>Next came a Grave Fellow with a Turbant almoſt as big as our
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Half Buſhel; at one ſide of it he had a Set of Diamonds, that did ſparkle as his Eyes; his Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture was green, his Legs were bare, on his Feet he did wear San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals.</p>
            <p>We had time to obſerve him as he entred the Door; for his Pace was ſlow and grave: I could have numbred 20 between every Step; He marcht in that manner to the upper end, where there was a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopy of State over his Head, and two Turky Carpets, with a large Pillow covered with Damask under him; he ſate upon it, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104773:18"/> and then the Owners of the Ship that took us, preſented themſelves before him, kiſſing the Hem of his Garment; they diſcourſed among themſelves about an hour, ſhewing unto him our Bills of Lading; a <hi>German</hi> of our Company under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſomething of their Diſcourſe, he told us that the King, who only ſate, all the reſt ſtanding about him, was diſpleaſed that they had not followed his Orders when they ſet out; for it ſeems he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to ſail along the Coaſt of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and to endeavour to revenge him for the great loſs which he had lately ſuſtained, when one of his beſt Veſſels that was ſent out upon his private account, was made Prize by the Galleys of that Republick.</p>
            <p>The Diſpute ended with the ſubmiſſion of the Owners of our Veſſel, and a Preſent very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104773:18"/> in Cloth and other rich Commodities taken out of our Prize.</p>
            <p>The Kings Diſpleaſure was ſoon abated, when he ſaw ſuch an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Gift enter into his Hall. He took a view of it, and then commanded us to come before him one by one; He look'd upon us with a ſtern Countenance, and took notice of our Features and Stature; for it ſeems the
<hi>Turks</hi> are excellent in the Art of Phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; they know a man and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations at the firſt view, as well as an expert Farrier can the good or ill Qualities of a Horſe: It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them much, eſpecially thoſe that trade in Slaves. He caſt a Jeſt upon every one of us, which gave the Company a great deal of Mirth, and increas'd our ſadneſs. I was inform'd that he ſaid, That he advis'd him that ſhould be my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104773:19"/> Maſter, not to truſt me too much with his Women.</p>
            <p>At laſt, when he had conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us all, he made us ſtand before him together; out of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he choſe my ſelf, the Skipper, and a pretty <hi>German</hi> Boy of a rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Countenance: I did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le wonder at this laſt Choice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were ſome of whom he might expect a greater Ranſom than of the Child, who was born of poor Parentage; but I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the good old man was a greater Lover of his Pleaſures than of Money, and therefore he pitcht upon him as upon one who might procure unto him ſome in his old Age; a ſtrange Fancy poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes the minds of all the Southern People; they burn with an unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Fire, which conſumed
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to ſee how paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104773:19"/> they are for handſom Males: I was glad to be in the poſſeſſion of the King, for I hoped to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him and get my Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to return for
<hi>England;</hi> but I was much deceived of my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, as you ſhall learn. The King being returned to his private Chambers ſent for me, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of my Quality, and of my Friends, and what Trade I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood beſt: I was puzzled at this laſt queſtion, and knew not how to anſwer him beſt for my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; I was afraid to render my ſelf too neceſſary to him, that he might not retain me in his ſervice; or to make my ſelf too conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that he might not put a higher value upon me than I was willing to pay for my Ranſom: Therefore I told him that I was born of poor Parentage, who not being able to keep me, put me to <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104773:20"/> be an Under-Cook to a Noble Man of our Country; that from that employment I was removed to be an Apprentice to a rich Merchant, who received me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he found me able to do him ſervice; and that I was ſent with his Goods to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and other Parts, as his Factor; that it was true, ſome of the Bills of Lading did mention my Name, but the Goods did belong to my Maſter, and ſome Friends who had intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me with them.</p>
            <p>I ſaw the Information pleaſed the old man, eſpecially when he heard I was a Cook; for one that had ſerved him in that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was lately dead. I was ſent immediately to the Kitchin, and had order to dreſs a Couple of Wild Ducks for my Maſter; that I did without much difficulty: but when I had other Meats leſs <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104773:20"/> uſual in our Country, I made ſuch mad Sauces, and ſuch ſtrange <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goux,</hi> that every one took me for a Cook of the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> whoſe People have Palates that reliſh things that ours abhor: I was full of Miſtakes; ſometimes I put Oyl inſtead of Vinegar, and Salt inſtead of Pepper. But that I might keep up my Credit amongſt the Beholders, I did handle my Meat ſo nimbly, that they all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved I had been uſed to Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery.</p>
            <p>I had not been long in the Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen, but I heard that the King lamented the Death of his former Cook, and was not pleaſed with the Sauces I had made; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I continued in my em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment about ſix Weeks, more eſteemed for my new-found miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſhes than I deſerved.</p>
            <p>At a great Feaſt that my Maſter <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104773:21"/> made, I had ſeveral ſorts of Fiſhes that I never ſaw before; the Liver of one hath a moſt loathſom taſt, I thought it good in the Sawce; therefore I ſent it up ſtewed under the Fiſh, with a Diſh garniſh'd with many ſorts of Flowers: The Gueſts ſeeing ſo pleaſant an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, expected the Fiſh to be as extraordinary as the Beauty; they all prepared their Stomachs to feed upon this Fiſh, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected others that were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but when they taſted the Sawce, they imagined ſome had put a Sir-reverence in it, and all began to ſpue and ſpit. I anger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much the King with this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece of Cookery, that he gave Order that I ſhould receive for my Sallery ten Baſtonadoes. It was in vain to plead Ignorance, &amp; our Country Faſhion; I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſuffer the puniſhment with Patience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104773:21"/>At the Feaſt there was an Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant of the Town who had been very much pleas'd with the Sauces that others did diſlike; when he ſaw the King ſo angry with me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to part with me for the uſual Ranſom; he refuſed it for the preſent: but afterwards he was glad to be rid of me at any rate.</p>
            <p>I was removed from being Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Cook to a lower place, &amp; a
<hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Slave was placed in my room. He did ſo domineer over me that I could not ſuffer his Impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: I plaid him ſeveral Tricks; once I made a ſtrange Infuſion in a Diſh that was to be preſented to the King; it almoſt coſt the Slaves Life; he excuſes, and laid the Fault upon me: I pretended a great deal of Ignorance, but was not believed. This cauſed my removal to another employment, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:104773:22"/> which I heartily longed for. I was made by a wonderful change of Fortune Keeper of the Kings Bath. It ſeems ſome of his Women had ſeen me in the Houſe, and interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for me when the laſt Diſgrace happened to me. I thought my ſelf then a pretty Fellow, and not inferiour to my former Eſtate; but Fortune left me not long rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing at my Promotion; her ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Favour was followed by a grievous Frown, that almoſt ſent me to my Grave: The occaſion of it was this; One of the Kings Wives having ſo happily pleaded for me, as the good man thought, out of a tenderneſs natural to all that Sex; and as ſhe then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, out of a Kindneſs for Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of my Nation, ſhe ſought a fit opportunity to diſcover her ſelf to me, and make uſe of my Bath when the King was abroad: I was at <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104773:22"/> firſt more reſpectful than ſhe did deſire, and left her to the Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of her Women Slaves; one that was her Confident, informed me of the Matter of her Miſtreſſes Pleaſure, and added, that I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould do well to comply, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry or diſappoint her Kindneſs by any ungrateful ſeverity.</p>
            <p>The Buſineſs came ſoon to the Kings Ear; his jealous Pate had an Eye upon a young Stripling that was not unworthy to ſupply his place; but it ſeems he never had a right Information, only ſome light ſuſpitions of our Correſpondency; they were ſufficient to cauſe him to remove me from my pleaſant Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; which angered me more than any thing that happened to me all the time of my Slavery.</p>
            <p>I found an opportunity to make my Complaints to my good Lady, who was no leſs troubled at the <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104773:23"/> old mans peeviſh humour than my ſelf.</p>
            <p>There was no Remedy to our Grief, but the hopes of meeting in ſome other Corner of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>I was ſent next to work in the Fields, where I met with ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and painful Labour, and ſuch cruel Task-Maſters, that I fell grievouſly ſick; my good Lady did not forget to adminiſter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort unto me by the means of her <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Woman: In my loweſt Eſtate ſhe vouchſafed to pay me a Viſit, and would not ſuffer me to want any thing that Credit could procure.</p>
            <p>It was a happineſs to me to meet here with ſuch a true Friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I could have wiſhed that my Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had laſted longer for her ſake.</p>
            <p>I was no ſooner recovered, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104773:23"/> my old doting Patron fearing a Relapſe, or rather growing more jealous of me, gave order that I ſhould be led into the Market-Place and there ſold: I had made my application to him to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, I had ſent Letters into <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be releaſed, but all in vain; he lookt upon me as ſo needy a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that could not procure the ordinary Ranſom of a Slave from my Friends. I had laboured to perſwade ſomething of it, during my abode in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>When I ſaw my ſelf with an ill-favoured <hi>Turk,</hi> leading me by a Chain, as a Horſe or a Bullock, thorough the ſtreets, I then began to lament my hard fortune, and remember my former Eſtate; I knew not what Providence had prepared for me, nor what ſurly Maſter I ſhould meet with next: <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104773:24"/> I went with a ſad Countenance, and as ſad a Heart to the publick Place, where I was to be expoſed to Sale.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turk</hi> that led me, cryed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me in <hi>Franca Langua, Who will buy a Chriſtian? Who will buy a Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a grievous change of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, in ſo ſhort a time as a year, to be reduced from that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eſtate in which my Father left me, to the loweſt Miſery, to a Slave, to be ſold as a Beaſt, in a ſtrange Countrey, where I had no Friends that did dare to own me. I muſt confeſs I was never ſo deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as at this time. I did complain of my hard Fate, and did ſend up many ſighs and groans to Heaven, to implore the aſſiſtance and care of Divine Providence: In this low Condition I knew not what it had prepared for me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104773:24"/>Aſſoon as I was come into the Market-place, a Fellow, a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to me, addreſſes himſelf to my Keeper, and offers Money for my Perſon: He ſeem'd to be a man of no great Appearance; yet his Looks diſcovered him to be a good man.</p>
            <p>Several others came about me, and amongſt the reſt, that ill-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd <hi>Engliſh</hi> Renegate that enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of our qualities ſo exactly on ſhipboard, accoſted my Keeper, and would needs have me at any Rate: I trembled for fear of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into his hands, knowing how grievouſly he had handled ſome of my Comrades.</p>
            <p>My Keeper made advantage of the Preſs, and ask'd a hundred Dollars more than he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take for me. The firſt would not let me ſlip out of his hands; therefore he paid the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104773:25"/> and led me away with him to a Houſe next to the Grand Moſque of the City, very near the Kings Palace.</p>
            <p>I was not a little pleas'd to be ſo near the Place from which I might expect ſome Aſſiſtance; much more, when I ſaw the good
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> Woman pay me a Viſit from her Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>It ſeems ſhe had ordered this Fellow to watch when I was to be ſold, and to buy me for her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. I thought my ſelf happy to be a Slave to ſo excellent and kind a Lady: I never dreamt of a Change whilſt I belonged unto her: I had no reaſon; for nothing was wanting unto me uſeful to the Life of Man. I only wore a Chain out of Formality, becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe my good Fortune might have been ſuſpected. I did alſo employ my ſelf in ſlaviſh work for that <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104773:25"/> intent, but not above meaſure.</p>
            <p>The Lady became very devout after my coming to that place; ſhe ſeldom miſs'd a day, but came in ſome Diſguiſe to pay her Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at the Moſquette, from whence there was a paſſage into my Lodgings,</p>
            <p>By this frequent and conſtant Attendance at Publick Prayer, ſhe purchas'd unto her ſelf a very great eſteem with the People, and a favour with her Husband; and ever after ſhe was named a Saint.</p>
            <p>I continued her Slave about two years, in which time I did view the City of <hi>Argiers,</hi> and took an eſpecial notice of many Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars worth the publick know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>It is a City not ſo large as popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, fortified by Art and Nature; the Walls are 60 foot high, in ſome places 70 and 80; they are built
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104773:26"/> with ſquare Stone and Flints: they are about 12 and 13 Foot broad.</p>
            <p>The City is not above a Mile round. At the Eaſt-ſide, on the top of a high Hill ſtands a ſtrong Cittadel very well fortified, built at firſt by the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> It is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with 40 or 50 Pieces of Ordnance, and kept by 300 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negadoes in Garriſon.</p>
            <p>At the Weſt ſide another Caſtle ſomewhat leſs, but altogether as ſtrong, doth overlook the Town. In the Harbour is built a very commodious Mould, able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain above 200 Sail. Upon it ſtands a ſtrong Fort, that threatens De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to all Veſſels that dare adventure near without leave, or in a Hoſtile manner: Three Tier of Guns are planted in it; the loweſt is level with the Water.</p>
            <p>The Mould lies in ſuch a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked manner, that no Ships can
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104773:26"/> with their full Sail come ſtraight in without turning: So that it is a very difficult work to break the Chain and enter it by force.</p>
            <p>This Neſt of Pirates is very well prepared for the Attempts of any Chriſtian Enemy. None can do them the leaſt injury by Land or by Sea: ſo that here they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat as the Wild Beaſts in their Dens to enjoy their Thefts and Prey.</p>
            <p>That which renders the Town more ſtrong, is, that it is built upon a hard Rock, and cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be undermined.</p>
            <p>I have taken notice of 3 Places in the Caſtles that are but weak; In the great Cittadel, on the South ſide, is a riſing Hill as high as the half of the Wall, if it was poſſeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a powerful Enemy, it might ſerve very commodiouſly either for Battery or Mining.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:104773:27"/>On the Eaſt ſide is but a weak Wall, that would not endure long the Fury of the Canon.</p>
            <p>The other Caſtle hath many lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Hills that are equal in height; beſides, the Wall in the Town in one place is not ſo ſtrong, but an Enemy might enter by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. attempted to drive theſe Pirates out of their Neſt, but it was to no purpoſe that he brought a Navy by Sea, and Landed a puiſſant Army to beſiege the Town; the violence of a ſtorm broke his Veſſels to pieces, and forced him to raiſe his Siege with the loſs of a hundred Ships, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand Men. Since that time
<hi>Argiers</hi> is much ſtronger, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fortified: Daily ſomething is added to the ſtrength of it; ſo that unleſs the Chriſtian Princes join together, or ſome powerful Monarch by Sea &amp; Land lay ſiege
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104773:27"/> to it, it will be one day impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but by Famine.</p>
            <p>In the City the Houſes are very pleaſant, and more beautiful with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without than in other Parts of <hi>Affrica.</hi> The greater lie open in the middle, with handſom Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries and Turrets.</p>
            <p>Several Moſquets are built for Publick Devotion, into which no Chriſtian hath liberty to enter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he intends to Apoſtatize; for he muſt either burn or turn that enters the Place of their Prayer, that handles the <hi>Alcoran</hi> before Witneſſes, or that repeats their <hi>Illa Alla Mahumet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They have a great number of their <hi>Talubs,</hi> Religious Men, whoſe Duty is to read their Publick Prayers. They have many other ſorts of Men appointed to attend in their <hi>Moſquets;</hi> ſome are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Law, and <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104773:28"/> they are called
<hi>Cadirs;</hi> others are to invite the People to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and they are named <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes;</hi> ſome live by the Alms of the People; others are Prophets and holy Men.</p>
            <p>Over all the Religious Orders there is one eſtabliſhed as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judge of all Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and he is honoured with the Title of
<hi>Marabut:</hi> He is the Judge between Man and Man, of Matters of Equity and Juſtice. A certain ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend is allowed unto him from the Publick Treaſury. He lives not upon the Inferiour Orders; every one hath a ſetled Salary. The great ſwallow the little ones, as Fiſhes; they feed upon them, and from their Labours derive a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to their idle Bodies: a ſad encouragement to Lazineſs &amp; Vice, and the grand Cauſe of the Diſorders of a Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104773:28"/>Other Perſons beſides the King and Baſhaw are eminent in this City; the <hi>Lagaw</hi> is the Chief in the next place, He is the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Duan,</hi> and is the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Armies abroad: Under him are the <hi>Cheuſes,</hi> which are like our Juſtices of Peace, or Sheriffs. The next are <hi>Boulgebuſhes,</hi> Men like our Bayliffs; they are Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the <hi>Duan:</hi> They remain three years in their Offices, and then go out with the Armies as Controulers of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, are other <hi>Buſhes,</hi> Captains and Officers of the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia; they wear a Badge of Honour on their Heads, and are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the reſt by their Turbant, that is wound about in the form of a Sugar-Loaf; behind a Red Croſs falls down: It is not lawful for any to take this At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire but themſelves. It is the <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104773:29"/> Badge of their Office, as the Red Scarf is the Sign of Command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>In the Camp there are other Great Men; as <hi>Daventees, Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Acha Baſha</hi> is an experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced man amongſt them, one that hath been in ſeveral Encounters, who commands a Party when it is ſeparated from the Main Body. He muſt be an old man, and when once he comes to that Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he can riſe no higher as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers can.</p>
            <p>About the City are moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Gardens, Orchards, and fair Houſes belonging to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
            <p>Further in the Countrey, very good Corn grows upon the little Hills that appear round about.</p>
            <p>Here is plenty of all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be of Wine, which is not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104773:29"/> made by the <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Moors.</hi> They of
<hi>Argiers</hi> are not ſo ſcrupulous as the ſtricter ſort; their Conſciences can ſuffer them to be drunk with Wine when they take good ſtore in Prizes.</p>
            <p>In the City, towards the Eaſt ſide, is a very ſtrong Houſe built, and ſome Souldiers to keep guard. I enquired what the Place was, and I was informed that it was the Publick Treaſury-Houſe: Every year they caſt in vaſt Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, according to their happineſs in the Encounters with Chriſtians. They never take out of it: It is thought there are many Millions ſhut up in that Hole. The laſt <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> built it for the Publick; and to encourage the reſt to give liberally, he put in 2000 Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars.</p>
            <p>When the Ships come in, and when the Lots are made, there is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104773:30"/> alwaies ſomething for the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a good Portion for <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems theſe Heathens have Religion enough to make them honour their Prophet, and thoſe that repreſent his Place amongſt them; for the moſt part ſuch are good for nothing elſe but to ſay the Publick Prayers: Yet the People are ſo far from deſpiſing them, that they bear a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto them; and ſuffer not any to be in want that attends at their Devotions.</p>
            <p>This Portion which is called the Portion of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prize-Goods, is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hands of a Treaſurer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe, and he diſtributes equally to all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men: If they find at any time that he hath converted the leaſt part to his private uſe, he is <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104773:30"/> put to death in a moſt cruel man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: He is ſtript naked, and at the Door of the <hi>Marabut</hi> he is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paled alive, and then in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner raiſed to the top of the Steeple of a <hi>Moſquet,</hi> where he is expoſed to Publick view for three daies; and then his Body is carried out of the City, to be given for food to the Wild Beaſts.</p>
            <p>His Eſtate is all ſold for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Religious Men; for they look upon it as conſecrated to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> when the leaſt part of what belongs to him hath been mingled amongſt it.</p>
            <p>This People hath wiſely provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt their Covetouſneſs &amp; diſorderly Behaviour, that rob or diminiſh from the Maintenance of thoſe Orders of Men that ſerve the Publick in the Worſhip of God, and that keep up the Honour of Religion amongſt them; for they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104773:31"/> are ſenſible that the preſervation of themſelves and Goverment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon their eſteem, their Credit and Proſperity, who only are able to perſwade men to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the eſtabliſh'd Laws; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are here moſt ſevere Puniſhments inflicted upon all thoſe that venture to injure ſuch either in their eſtates or Perſons. And there is very good proviſion made that they may not fall into the diſeſteem of the People.</p>
            <p>There are excellent Orders to ſtir them up to the Service of God: they are often ſummoned to Prayers; In the Morning, which time they call
<hi>Salam,</hi> at Twelve of the Clock, named <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char,</hi> at Four in the Afternoon is their <hi>Aſſara;</hi> at Sun-ſetting, <hi>Mog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harb;</hi> at Twilight, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher;</hi> at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night is <hi>Ou-el;</hi> the next is
<hi>Iſtanay:</hi> At theſe ſeveral times great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104773:31"/> of all ſorts do reſort to their <hi>Moſquets,</hi> and there in an humble manner they pray to God and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that are negligent or careleſs in coming to Prayer, are taken notice of, and if they have been formerly Chriſtians, they are excluded from all hopes of Employment, and at the leaſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſeverely treated.</p>
            <p>The Ceremonies obſerved in the Conſecration of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men are not unworthy of our Notice; The Father of the young man muſt bring him to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabut,</hi> when he ſits in the Chief
<hi>Moſquet</hi> of the City with a numorous Attendance, to be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his Dedication to that Service. They enter the Place, the Father holding the Son by the Right hand, and both together go ſtraight to the <hi>Marabut,</hi> and kiſs <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104773:32"/> the Border of his Robe. After this Ceremony, the <hi>Marabut</hi> asks the Father whether he can read; the Father anſwers, Yes. A Book is immediately preſented to the young Fellow, uſually the
<hi>Alcoran,</hi> who reads in it a Page: If he doth not miſs a word, but pronounce well and diſtinctly, he is then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: The <hi>Marabut</hi> calls him by his Name, and cauſeth it to be enrolled in the Catalogue of the Order: Then comes a Fellow with a ſharp Knife, and cuts in his Right Arm the Figure of a half Moon; into the Wound is put ſome Gunpowder, which being blown up, leaves a blew Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that nothing can take away, unleſs the place be cut off.</p>
            <p>Afterwards ſome Prayers being made, tending to the Confirmation of him into their Holy Orders, he is obliged to ſwear by <hi>Mahomets</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104773:32"/> Lock of Hair to obſerve certain Rules.</p>
            <p>He is then cloathed in another manner before the People, and the
<hi>Marabut</hi> takes him into his Arms, and gives him a Kiſs, which ſanctifies him for ever; the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ends in Muſick and Dancing. This is practiſed at their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into that Rank of Men which they eſteem holy, and who only may publickly read the <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay nothing of their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and Circumciſions, their Cuſtoms are not much different from the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did obſerve many particulars in the Happy time of my Slavery, for I had liberty to view the City, and to walk up and down; my buſineſs and work was only to wait upon my Lady at the time of her Devotions, ſometimes it was at <hi>Moghar,</hi> and ſometimes <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104773:33"/> in the Day at <hi>Dochar.</hi> I did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my ſelf to her, and told her of the happineſs of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Life in our Countrey; I laboured to perſwade her to eſcape out of the old Mans reach; I promiſed my Aſſiſtance, and that if ſhe would conſent unto it, I ingaged my ſelf to her to Marry her. She had two Children, a Boy and a Girl, that kept her in that place, otherwiſe I think I had then got my Freedom and carryed her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; but ſhe would not for that cauſe hearken to my perſwaſions, nor ſuffer me to talk of my Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, telling me, that I ſhould want nothing whilſt I remained in that place, and in her ſervice; that if I rendred my ſelf unworthy of it, by offering to run away, I ſhould become the moſt miſerable of all men.</p>
            <p>I was ever after more humble <pb n="57" facs="tcp:104773:33"/> and dutiful, and was afraid ſhe ſhould diſcover in me an inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be gone.</p>
            <p>During this time I received ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Letters from <hi>Cadiz, Malaga,</hi> and other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factories, that mentioned my Redemption, but I could never expect to obtain it from my kind Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>About that time ſhe departed this Life, and left me ſufficient cauſe to lament: Another of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Wives was ſuſpected to have poyſoned her, becauſe the <hi>Sultan</hi> had conceived a greater Love for her, by reaſon of her conſtant Devotions, than for the other. Before her Death, about ſix moneths, ſhe was brought to Bed of a pretty little Girl, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what whiter than ordinary; the old Fool thought himſelf to be the Father of it. I was once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſee it; but now my
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104773:34"/> Miſtreſs was dead, I was left to the Misfortunes and Miſeries of a ſlaviſh Life. I was forced again to return to a hard Service, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though her Goodneſs had labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to free me; for ſhe ſent to the man at whoſe houſe I lay, being her Couſin German, to ſpeak with him before her Death: She did then make him promiſe to give me my Releaſe after her Burial in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital of my good Service, and by her Gentlewoman ſent me a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Gold, to a conſiderable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, which I did not poſſeſs long. You may eaſily imagine my grief to part with ſo true a Friend: It was not a little increas'd when I perceiv'd the Fellow would not perform his Couſins requeſt; but inſtead of ſending me away, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to the Market again to be ſold. I did long expoſtulate the buſineſs with him, but could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104773:34"/> have other Reaſons of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding but this, That I ſhould not anger him for fear he ſhould publiſh the Myſtery, which would infallibly coſt me my Head.</p>
            <p>I was forced to ſubmit to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt pleaſure. He led me to the Market, and there I was ſold for 300 Dollars; for I never made my ſelf known to him; he always look'd upon me as a pitiful Fellow, unable to redeem my ſelf.</p>
            <p>My next Maſter was by Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a Gardener, he had me into his Orchards, and there with a good Cudgel he made me under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a trade I never knew before. I endured much with him; for he gave me ſuch great Tasks to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, that I was not able to hold out.</p>
            <p>At the leaſt diſpleaſure he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtab and kill me; therefore the fear of Death made me ſeek <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104773:35"/> my efcape. I was ſometimes ſent to fetch Lime for a Building that he had in hand near the Sea-ſhore. A Veſſel was lately arrived from <hi>France,</hi> to redeem the Captives; it lay without the Mould.</p>
            <p>At that time that I was on the Sand it was dusky, a
<hi>French</hi> man offered me his aſſiſtance, I accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of it, and went into his Boat; but I was diſcovered before I could get off the Mould, and ſent back to my Maſter, that puniſhed me with a hundred blows on the Soles of my Feet, which rendred me uncapable for his Service many days.</p>
            <p>He was ſoon weary of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſold me to the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Renegado that came on board our Ship at our Arrival. I expected from him a kinder entertainment, but found leſs: He was cruel and ſevere to me, he made me work <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104773:35"/> night and day. I often treated with him for my Ranſom, but found his Demands to be ſo high, that I could not comply with him. He abus'd me moſt ſadly about five Moneths, and then Death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me of his Tyranny.</p>
            <p>His Executors ſold me again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Goods and Chattels. I fell next inro the hands of an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Renegado, named <hi>Iſhmael Reiz,</hi> who was not kinder to me than my former Maſters; my Work was painful, my Diet mean, my Labour continual, and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Blows of a hard Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</p>
            <p>I could not ſuffer long this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; therefore I ſought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe my Patron, and make him ſell me to another.</p>
            <p>He gave me next to an Officer of the Militia called <hi>Hally Hamez Reiz,</hi> who was ſo well pleaſed <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104773:36"/> with my Perſon and Countenance, that he reſolved not to part with me for any Money. I offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him 800 Dollars: He told me I ſhould firſt go with him in the Countrey, and at his return I ſhould have liberty to be redeem'd if I behaved my ſelf well.</p>
            <p>At that time the <hi>Turks</hi> did ſend out a ſtrong Army to gather the Contributions of the People, and to relieve <hi>Tremſen</hi> or
<hi>Climſan,</hi> a ſtrong and populous City in the Country.</p>
            <p>There is a Garriſon of <hi>Turks</hi> that are ſent every year to that place, and another that comes from thence; for as it is a great City, the Countrey round about do always ſubmit to thoſe that are Maſters of that Place. It concerns therefore the <hi>Turks</hi> to fortifie and preſerve that City for themſelves againſt the Attempts of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104773:36"/> that are their deadly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Having run through ſo many ſtrange and unexpected Fortunes, I did not hope to meet with leſs Variety in this Expedition, in the which I was engaged amongſt the reſt; my Maſter was a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a hundred Men: He was very paſſionate and laſcivious, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs Valiant; as I did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards learn.</p>
            <p>We marched out in very good Order, with our Flying Colours and ſome few Field-Pieces very ſmall.</p>
            <p>The Army was compoſed of Twelve Thouſand Men; Four Thouſand were to go Weſtward, and gather the contributions along the Sea-Coaſt as far as <hi>Tetuan</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Fez:</hi> The next Four Thouſand were to march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Tunis;</hi> and the third Four
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104773:37"/> Thouſand were to enter into the Country.</p>
            <p>The Cuſtom of the <hi>Turks</hi> is to gather the Contributions upon the Inhabitants who do not pay wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; therefore they venture not amongſt them but in great Numbers, well armed, able to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Enemy, or prevent a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſurprizal. There is a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Antipathy between them. The <hi>Moors</hi> that dwell in the Kingdom, and the <hi>Arabs</hi> do hate the <hi>Turks,</hi> becauſe they are imperious, and and becauſe they are obliged to pay unto them an yearly Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute.</p>
            <p>The time that theſe Armies ſet forth was in <hi>June,</hi> the Harveſt, when the Corn was ripe and fit for uſe: then the Country was able to furniſh the yearly Revenue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Corn or Money.</p>
            <p>The Commander of the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern <pb n="65" facs="tcp:104773:37"/> Circuit was
<hi>Abel Hamed Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> of the Eaſtern were two Chieftains, <hi>Halac Rigla Reiz,</hi> an old Renegado of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Halec Sim Haly,</hi> a young Blade that had more Precipitation than Wiſdom; they met with many Miſchances, as you ſhall afterwards hear, and had it not been for our unexpected Approach, the whole Army had been cut in pieces.</p>
            <p>Our Commander was a judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, but very unfortunate; cruel, bold and valiant, a great Enemy of the <hi>Arabs;</hi> his Name was <hi>Ben Oſman Bucher,</hi> he had been a great Commander at Sea, and fought in many notable Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt the Chriſtians, never with ſo much ſucceſs as in the Year 36. againſt a <hi>Portugueſe Caraque,</hi> near the Iſland of <hi>Tenerifa,</hi> ſayling from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and bound for <hi>Lisbon,</hi> laden with very rich <pb n="66" facs="tcp:104773:38"/> Commodities to a great value. His ſhare was ſo conſiderable, that he was raiſed from a poor and a mean Eſtate to a good Fortune, and to the Eſteem of the <hi>Divan;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally becauſe the good Succeſs of that Fight was attributed to his Valour and Reſolution: For the <hi>Christians</hi> making a ſtout reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the <hi>Turks</hi> were diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from further Attempts, and not willing to continue their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize longer, when he with his drawn Cymeter did compel ſome, and perſwade others to try again the <hi>Portuguez</hi> Courage, and ſo by that means won the Ship, and brought great Riches into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: He was ever after highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, and employed in great Affairs where any danger or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty did appear. For that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he commanded the Army that was to go the middle Circuit; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104773:38"/> there are a ſort of People very valiant and ſtout, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make a ſtrong Reſiſtance to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and when they ſee their advantage, they refuſe Tribute.</p>
            <p>Our Army was compoſed of Horſe and Foot; a thouſand Horſe, and two thouſand Foot were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred at the Muſters, beſides Slaves and Servants.</p>
            <p>The Cavalry was compoſed of <hi>Turks</hi> born, and
<hi>Moors</hi> that had quitted their Countreys intereſt to ſerve them of
<hi>Argiers;</hi> and for the moſt part they were Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the City, and had there their Wives and Children.</p>
            <p>The Infantry was made up of Renegado-Chriſtians, whereof there are ſuch number in that place, that they bear all the ſway and command both by Sea and Land. They are as Imperious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the reſt as the
<hi>Janizaries</hi> in <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104773:39"/> 
               <hi>Turky</hi> over the
<hi>Greeks,</hi> and the <hi>Mamalukes</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> were over the ancient Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Divan</hi> is compoſed of this ſort of men, who are moſt skilful becauſe they are acquainted with the Affairs of
<hi>Europe,</hi> and better able to manage the Publick Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs relating to that part of the World, and to give Orders. Some of them do get vaſt Eſtates, others are miſerable and poor, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are obliged to the meaneſt Offices.</p>
            <p>With this ſtrong Party we ſet forward, and came to a Place the firſt day called <hi>Atſabah,</hi> at two Leagues diſtance from the Sea: It was a pretty little Town ſituate on the Decline of a pleaſant Hill, that was covered on the right hand with a Large Wood, extream Buſhy, about two Miles in length. The Houſes were more handſom <pb n="69" facs="tcp:104773:39"/> than we could expect in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey Village. About it were to be ſeen the Ruines of old Buildings that did only appear out of the Earth. A Chriſtian Renegado that had ſtudied in the Univerſity of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> informed me, that this place was named anciently <hi>Stilpeia,</hi> and that it had been an Epiſcopal See in the time of the Chriſtian Churches.</p>
            <p>The Chief man of the place was a <hi>Turk,</hi> retired from the Affairs and Noiſe of the City, here he was reſolved to ſpend the reſt of his days, that were not very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; for I conceive he was above fourſcore.</p>
            <p>We lodged that night about this little Town. Round about
<hi>Argeirs</hi> there are many ſuch, at ſome diſtance from the place.</p>
            <p>The next morning we marched by break of Day, and went five
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104773:40"/> Leagues before we did reſt. We paſſed by the Tents of many <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs,</hi> who had gathered all their Corn. The Chief of every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily paid our Receiver in Dollars and Gold, whereof there is a great quantity all along the Sea-Coaſt. They informed our General that a ſmall number of their Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were met together, and were reſolved to diſpute unto us the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a River.</p>
            <p>This News made us ſtand upon our Guards, and was the occaſion of frequent Alarms given to our Camp; for at the ſight of a few Horſemen, we did imagine the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to be at their Heels, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to charge us.</p>
            <p>This days Journey was very pleaſant; for although I had my Maſters Lance, and a Gun to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on my Shoulder, our Victuals that we brought with us were not <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104773:40"/> yet ſpent, the way was very good, and we had ſeveral Accidents that we met with, that gave us a great deal of ſport; beſides I had acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted an <hi>Engliſh Turk,</hi> with whom I did entertain my ſelf of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of our Nation; I found him deſirous to ſeek his eſcape, becauſe he had not lighted upon ſo good a Fortune as others in their Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and becauſe he had been put by an Employment that he had ſought after; and I think his Conſcience did a little trouble him to have obſcured that Truth that he knew to be ſo; therefore when I took the liberty to lay it before his Eyes, he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his Tears.</p>
            <p>Our General had no difficulty this day; for ſeveral came and brought in at the place appointed theit uſual Tribute. The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are ſo near the City, and have <pb n="72" facs="tcp:104773:41"/> ſo great a dependency upon it, that they are affraid to diſoblige it in the leaſt. Therefore when thoſe other people that were in Arms, did think to revolt from the
<hi>Turks,</hi> they ſent ſome to ſollicite theſe to join with them. They did all wiſh to be delivered from the <hi>Turks</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, but they were affraid to venture, becauſe their near Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations were likely to ſuffer firſt the <hi>Turks</hi> Vengeance and Fury.</p>
            <p>The Country we found very fruitful of Corn and Fodder. As we paſſed by a Wood, we had the ſight of ſeveral Wild Beaſts that returned from ſeeking their Prey. Our Van-guard did ſhoot at many of them; one of our Company, to ſhew his Valour, met a Lion that advanc'd towards us, and with his Cymeter in his hand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred him: The ſport almoſt coſt the Fellow his Life, for the <pb n="73" facs="tcp:104773:41"/> Lion was very ſtrong, and with his Paws he had twice ſtruck him down, the laſt time the Lion in a rage had bit off part of his Arm; he had inſtantly devoured him, had not we all ſhot at him, &amp; fixed above 100 Bullets in his Body. The Fellow we found almoſt dead with fear, under the Lion. He was glad with the loſs of ſome of his Fleſh, to be ſo happily eſcap'd; none pitied him, or was ſorry for his wounds, his raſh Enterprize did deſerve no leſs.</p>
            <p>We journeyed about three Leagues, and we came to a little Valley very fruitful of Palms and Olive Trees, a ſmall Rivulet, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Strawberry Buſhes, did run through it, and water the Plain; at each end a Grove did grow.</p>
            <p>In one, as we paſſed, I ſaw a Flying Serpent, about the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104773:42"/> bigneſs of an ordinary Dog, with a long Tail, and a Head like an Ape, with a larger mouth, and a long Tongue, the Body had about four Foot in length; we ſhot at it, but could not kill it: It threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome of our men when they ventured to come near it, and could not be obliged to depart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til a great number of us were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the Place. I ſaw it near a pleaſant Fountain that did riſe in one ſide of the furthermoſt Grove. I enquired of the Name, but could not learn it; it had Wings of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Colours, the chief were Red and White: It hovered long o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our heads, and had not the Noiſe of our Guns frighted it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I think it had ventured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us again. I could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh of what ſubſtance the Wings were; they were bigger than thoſe of our winged Fowls; <pb n="75" facs="tcp:104773:42"/> all the Birds that ſaw it at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance were glad to fly. I imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to be a kind of Baſilisk, a deſperate Serpent, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Venomous. This ſight was no leſs wonderful to the reſt than to me; for all profeſſed to have never ſeen the like: That made me believe it was ſome In-land Creature not uſually ſeen near the Sea-Coaſt.</p>
            <p>We met in this Journey nothing elſe remarkable, but ſome Ancient Pillars of Marble; upon one I ſaw ſome <hi>Arabick</hi> Letters; A
<hi>Moor</hi> told me that they ſignified the Name of a great Commander that won a Battel fighting againſt the Inhabitants, when he led the
<hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> into that Country, <hi>I</hi> Zidi Dockra Moukadem <hi>under the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned General and Prince</hi> Abel Hamed, <hi>do erect this Pillar in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of a great Victory obtained of <pb n="76" facs="tcp:104773:43"/> the</hi> Brabbers,
<hi>in the which I kill'd their Commander with my own Hands, whoſe Name was</hi> Azoret Moudem; <hi>he was followed by</hi> 6000 <hi>Stout Souldiers; I had only</hi> 2000 <hi>of my Countrey-men; but our good Prophet would not ſuffer us to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by his Enemies; he lent us a favourable Aſſiſtance, and in one hours time we deſtroyed</hi> 3582 <hi>with the loſs of</hi> 37 <hi>of my Men, and of the</hi> Hageria 130.</p>
            <p>About a League farther we met with ſeveral Heaps of Stones, and near unto them, in the way ſide, a large Cave, into the which, with my Maſters Leave, I entered: It was hewn out of a Rock, there were ſeveral Chambers about five Foot broad, and as many long; there was nothing remarkable but ſeveral heaps of Bones: It ſeems the Wild Beaſts did make it their Retreat when they had ſeized on <pb n="77" facs="tcp:104773:43"/> their Prey. I imagined it to be a Place made for the Dwelling of ſome ſolitary <hi>Anachoret</hi> of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, retired out of the World into that remote place. That which confirmed me in this Belief, was a great Number of Croſſes and Crucifixes artificially made in the Rock, in the inner Chamber, which had no other Light but that which entered in by Reflections from the Caves Mouth through the other Rooms. I had only time to look upon this Religious Place; for the coming up of the Rear haſtened me away. That Night we reach'd as far as <hi>Boumelli,</hi> a good Town ſituate upon a River ſide, very pleaſant becauſe of the Medows that did encompaſs it, and ſeveral little Hills that were to be ſeen afar off, crowned with Orange and Limon Trees that are always green in <pb n="78" facs="tcp:104773:44"/> thoſe Countries. The Inhabitants furniſhed us with all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and when our Army began to approach, they came in a very humble manner to pay homage to our Commander in Chief; the <hi>Shack</hi> of the Place went in the Head of them on foot, and kiſs'd the Hem of our Generals Garment, and preſented unto him a Basket full of Loaves, two white Cows, and half a dozen young Barbs. The Preſent was accepted, and they were confirmed in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Lands.</p>
            <p>There were in the Town about 600 Houſes or Huts; ſome were pretty conſiderable, and adorned with Marble Pillars, and good Workmanſhip.</p>
            <p>They were moſt Graziers; for we found hereabouts ſeveral Droves of Cattel very fat.</p>
            <p>The Country People informed <pb n="79" facs="tcp:104773:44"/> us of the Deſign of the <hi>Arabs</hi> to reſiſt us: They were gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether beyond the River <hi>Talna,</hi> where they were reſolved to try the Fortune of a Battel: All their Subſtance they had tranſported to the Top of a high Mountain, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Inhabitants <hi>Azar,</hi> unto which they were reſolved to flee, if they did loſe the Day.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of their Revolt, as was pretended, was the
<hi>Turks</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, the Poverty of the Year not able to furniſh for their own Livelihood, and for the Tribute demanded from them; therefore they had made haſte to gather up the Corn, and had prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to make reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>This kind of People did not want a Reſolution to fight, nor good Conduct in the management of their Affairs; for they had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd away ſeveral Meſſengers <pb n="80" facs="tcp:104773:45"/> into the Neigbouring Countries for Aid, and had drawn a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to their Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Our General gave notice of all things to the other Armies, that they might draw towards him, if Occaſion did require it: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he proceeded in his March, and did ſend every day ſeveral Parties of Horſe from the main Body to receive the Offerings of the People.</p>
            <p>The third day, which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Account the 20th of
<hi>June,</hi> we paſt over high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains fenced on all ſides with crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy Rocks; we were obliged ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to climb over them: Our Horſe took a compaſs about by a way more eaſie.</p>
            <p>About Noon the Sun was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hot, which obliged us to ſeek a Repoſe under the ſhady Trees that grew in this Stony
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104773:45"/> ground; as I was reſting my ſelf at a diſtance from my Patrons Company, a great Scorpion ſpies me in her way, and as I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſleeping and waking, the venomous Creature fixed her ſting in my naked Leg ſo gently that I had not felt it, had not my next Neighbour advertiſed me. I had heard much of that Beaſt; when I ſaw my ſelf wounded by it, and my fleſh ſwelling, immediately I began to fear the increaſe of the Venom, but ſome had already kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, and brought the Blood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me to apply to the Wound. It was wonderful to ſee the preſent cure that the Blood gave; it had no ſooner touch'd the tumor, but it began to decreaſe, and out of the little prick came forth a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor white as Milk, by that I found that the blood of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion hath an attractive virtue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:104773:46"/>I had no ſooner eſcaped this Miſchief, but I fell into a worſe; my Maſter had ſent me to the Rear to buy Victuals for himſelf; for there were ſome in that place that did ſell Bread and Meat ready dreſs'd: As I was returning load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I fell down with my burden a ſteep Rock, and bruiſed my ſelf; but the fear leſt my Maſter ſhould cudgel me for my Misfortune, rouzed me up, and made me ſpeed towards him.</p>
            <p>From this unhappy place we removed up Hill through a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that was not inhabited, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be by Monſters and Wild Beaſts, whereof we ſaw a great many; ſome not known to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>It ſeems the Deſign of our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral was to ſurprize the
<hi>Arabian</hi> Army on a ſudden, and to come upon them by a way that they leaſt <pb n="83" facs="tcp:104773:46"/> ſuſpected. We marched here through Woods, over Rocks and Hills three days together. I had the ſatisfaction for my pains to ſee ſeveral Creatures; of which I ſhall give a brief Account.</p>
            <p>This Mountain is part of the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> it runs all along through this Kingdom, and that of <hi>Fez,</hi> and reaches as far as the main Ocean; ſome part of it is very high.</p>
            <p>We came to a place in this hot time of Summer, which was very cold: In the Corners that were not expoſed to the Sun was a great deal of Ice and Snow. This place which gave us a Proſpect over all the Countrey, was in the ſecond Region of the Air.</p>
            <p>Here we found plenty of woods and Trees, and ſeveral ſorts of Birds; one we did kill that had four Legs as a Beaſt: Its Body was as big as a Turkie-Cock, the <pb n="84" facs="tcp:104773:47"/> Head was like an Owl, its Tail was extream broad, the Plumes were grey, and the Head only black; it did not fly very ſwiftly, therefore our people had not much difficulty to kill it.</p>
            <p>We ſaw ſeveral ſorts of Lions; towards the Evening they did go out of their Dens, when the <hi>Jac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kals</hi> began to bark.</p>
            <p>The nobleſt ſort of Lion is that which is called the
<hi>Royal;</hi> it is the biggeſt and the ſtrongſt ſort; it hath a Shape ſomewhat differing from the reſt, and a Voice more ſtout: When any of the others do meet ſuch an one, they ſeem to yield a reſpect unto him. He is more grave in his Motion, more fierce in the Encounter, undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the greateſt danger.</p>
            <p>There are other ſorts of a leſſer Size. Every night we were viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſeveral Companies of wild <pb n="85" facs="tcp:104773:47"/> Creatures; ſome had the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to break in upon us, but theſe never returned again to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to tell News.</p>
            <p>In an Evening we diſcovered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off a great Beaſt; ſome of us went nearer to it to diſcharge our Guns at it: It was a Monſter of a large Bulk, the Head was like a Lion, the Paws like a Bear, the hinder parts much like to an Aſs; when it was killed, every one in the Army had a ſight of it; I then did remember the Saying of the <hi>Romans, Africa ſemper apportat ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid novi;</hi> every year there is ſome ſtrange Creature or other to be ſeen in theſe remote places.</p>
            <p>Some make it their buſineſs to watch them at the Seaſon of the Year that they uſually come into the World, and employ all their Art to catch them, that they might lead them from place to place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:104773:48"/> to ſhew them to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants for money.</p>
            <p>There are here a great number of wild Goats, we had the ſight of ſome that climbed up the ſteepy Rocks, but could not come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Shot of them.</p>
            <p>Another Creature I ſaw here much like unto a Dog, very nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quick ſighted, but yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extraordinary ſtink; it is called by the Moore <hi>Subſib.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo another of the ſame ſhape, only this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that it hath a white Tail, and adventures in the night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Inhabitants to ſteal the Good-wives Hens and Geeſe; it is called
<hi>Thaloub;</hi> it is of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Foxes, very ſubtil and crafty.</p>
            <p>I ſaw here in this wild place ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other ſorts of Serpents and Beaſts, of which I could not come <pb n="87" facs="tcp:104773:48"/> near to take a full view, therefore I ſhall not adventure to deſcribe them.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot one of a ſtrange Nature; it appear'd unto us as a White Lamb, ſomething differing in the ſhape, as we were marching through a Valley; but when it perceived us to approach in ſuch Numbers, it fled before us; our Captain thought it had been ſome ſtragling Lamb belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome Mountainous People, and becauſe we were not well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with good Victuals, he ſent ſome of us to overtake it before it got into the neighbouring thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of a riſing Hill: I had Order to purſue it, and accompany the Hunters. As we came within a hundred Paces of it, it made more haſte than ordinary, and began to ſhift for it ſelf amongſt the Trees; but as it could not well eſcape <pb n="88" facs="tcp:104773:49"/> from us, becauſe it was already weary, and very fat, we overtook it at the entry in of the Buſhes; but perceiving us ſo near, it ran under one, and that we might not find it, it changed in an inſtant its white colour into the ſame with the Buſh, which unexpected alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration gave us a great deal of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. We had never found it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, had not one of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcharged a Musket; at the Noiſe it roſe up in a fright, and began to run for its Life; we lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thought it to be the ſame, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſome of us did venture after it, and ſome remained in the place, ſeeking the white Beaſt: The Purſuers ſhot off one of its Legs, and then cried to us to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſeeking, and that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Lamb was caught. We went to be Eye witneſſes of the Wonder; it was the ſame ſhap'd <pb n="89" facs="tcp:104773:49"/> Beaſt, but the colour was no more White as before, the Milky Colour was changed into a Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Gray: Its Coat was a fine Wool, the Head was like a Wolf, not altogether ſo long, it had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſharp Teeth, and a fierce Look, the Hinder-parts were like a Sheep: It is one of the ſtrangeſt Creatures I ever ſaw. I wondred how it could alter its White Wool into a Colour ſo different: I imagined this to be the Beaſt mentioned by the Learned, that takes the Colour of the place where it lays; a good Emblem of an Hypocrite.</p>
            <p>We ſpent three days climbing over theſe mountainous places, and fighting with ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Creatures to me: But as this was not the buſineſs we inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, we made haſte into the plain Countrey; our Horſe and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages <pb n="90" facs="tcp:104773:50"/> we had ſent by another way, a little about, ſo we arrived at the Paſſage of the River before them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Arabs</hi> ſlept in great ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, little thinking that we would adventure over the Mountains and Rocks.</p>
            <p>Our General Commanded us to reſt, and fit our ſelves for Action, for he imagined, that aſſoon as we ſhould come into the Plain, our arrival would be known to the Enemies, and that they would not fail to make Attempts upon us on a ſuddain. We refreſhed our ſelves all that Evening, until the next Morning, when an Alarum was ſounded, at the which we all ran to our Arms, and put our ſelves in order, expecting the On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of ſome
<hi>Arabs,</hi> but no Enemy appeared, unleſs it was a company of Apes purſued by a few Jaccals, <pb n="91" facs="tcp:104773:50"/> who made ſuch a noiſe in the Wood that was near us, running up and down the Branches, that thoſe upon the skirts of the Army thought them to be the Enemy, that took the advantage of the place to fire upon us; their need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Fear did aſſoon appear as the nimble Creatures recover'd the tops of the higheſt trees, to whoſe protection they did dare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves; nevertheleſs the Allarm continued, and ran, as nimbly as the Apes, all over the Army, it could not be ſtopt until every one was informed of the cauſe of the Fright.</p>
            <p>We Marched all that Morning until Noon, and then came to the foot of the Hills, where our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral was reſolved to ſtay till E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, intending with a Party at Midnight to fall upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who was not above ſix Miles <pb n="92" facs="tcp:104773:51"/> diſtance from us: as it began to dawn, we advanc'd, and found ſome few Tents ſtragling from the reſt; the
<hi>Arabs</hi> that were in them, told us that the main Body was at the Ford of the River <hi>Tafna,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting our Arrival; that they had broken down all the Bridges all along, and were reſolved to fight us; they further informed us of the cauſe of their Revolt: A Perſon of a Noble Family of one of their Tribes, named <hi>Iſha Muker,</hi> whoſe Parents had been very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the Kingdom of <hi>Fez,</hi> was that year come amongſt them, with all his Subſtance; that he was look'd upon as an Eminent Commander, skilful in Affairs of War and Peace, and that he was therefore well received, becauſe alſo that he was very rich; That this was the man had perſwaded them to ſhake off the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> yoke.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:104773:51"/> At firſt they were timorous and fearful to revolt; but at laſt he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them, by repreſenting how imperious they were, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of the Year, that could not furniſh the Tribute-Money, and to their ſubſiſtency. Beſides he told them that the <hi>Turks</hi> were not true
<hi>Mahometans,</hi> that they were He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical in their Opinions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane in their Practices, and that it was not lawful to ſubmit to, and own ſuch for their Maſters. Theſe Reaſons had work'd upon the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, but could not cauſe them to take up Arms until he had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd himſelf of this Stratagem; A Fellow was lately come into thoſe Parts from <hi>Mecha,</hi> and feigned to be lame; His Pilgrimage was much more eſteemed becauſe of the pretended Impediment of his Feet.</p>
            <p>Before he was arrived, <hi>Elmſwar <pb n="94" facs="tcp:104773:52"/> Tapnez,</hi> for that was the Noble Mans Name, had ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him how he ſhould behave himſelf: He brought with him a Letter which was directed to the Chief Leading men of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, from the Keeper of
<hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi>'s Temple; the Contents were, That <hi>Mahomet</hi> had appear'd unto him in a Dream, and commanded him to ſignifie unto them that it was his Pleaſure to aſſiſt them this year in a notable manner, and free them from the Slavery of the <hi>Turk:</hi> It promiſed beſides the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Heaven to thoſe that ſhould be valiant, and eternal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to the Cowards and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient.</p>
            <p>This Letter was given almoſt at the ſame time to the Grandees, and divulged all abroad amongſt the <hi>Arabs</hi> in the Kingdom; ſome did give credit to it, others did look <pb n="95" facs="tcp:104773:52"/> upon it as an Impoſture. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs an Aſſembly was called of the Chief of them, where the Letter being again produc'd in the preſence of <hi>Tapnez,</hi> the
<hi>Hage</hi> or Religious Pilgrim ſeeing him come in, fell on his Face and kiſs'd the hem of his Garment; the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants wondred at this humility, not uſual in perſons of that Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, until he had told them the Cauſe: He affirmed that the Great Prophet had appeared that night unto him, and in conſideration of his great pains he had ſuffered in his Travels to <hi>Meccha,</hi> he would cure him of his Lameneſs, that he had ſhew'd him the Perſon in his ſhape that ſhould lay his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and cure him, and that it was this ſame man that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: <hi>Tapnez</hi> ſeem'd to increaſe the number of the Wonderers, and would not be perſwaded the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation <pb n="96" facs="tcp:104773:53"/> had been real, until the
<hi>Hage</hi> or Holy Man with all the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly earneſtly requeſted him to try what he was able to do: At laſt he conſented to their Prayers, and with his Right Hand began to ſtroke the Lame man.</p>
            <p>He no ſooner felt the others ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but he began to leap, and falling at his Feet, adored him as a Holy Man.</p>
            <p>The Aſſembly taking notice of the Cure, and the manner of it, did really believe the <hi>Hage,</hi> and without delay eſtabliſhed
<hi>Tapnez</hi> for their General and Chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, until they could give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their Deſignes to ſome of the Blood-Royal of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who only may command over them as King or Emperor. It was then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved alſo that they would no longer pay Tribute to the <hi>Turk: Tapnez</hi> confirmed his Credit by <pb n="97" facs="tcp:104773:53"/> many other feigned Miracles; ſo that he was look'd upon in the the Countrey as ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fellow ſent from Heaven to their Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>He had gathered together thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand Horſe and Foot; the Countrey People reported more: and with this Army was reſolved to wait for the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army that came that way to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Contributions, and to relieve the Garriſon of <hi>Chinſan</hi> or <hi>Tremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> a City in the middle of the Countrey, not inferiour to <hi>Fez.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Numbers of our Enemies did ſtartle us when we heard how they were reſolved to revenge themſelves for all paſt Affronts; therefore the Commanders did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the General not to expoſe them to ſo eminent a danger until the other Armies had joined with him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:104773:54"/>His Courage was great, he could not yield to this wholſom advice; his Hopes were greater: He was reſolved to get all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Victory to himſelf; therefore he propoſed to fall upon the
<hi>Arabs</hi> that night; he ſhewed it to his Captains, to perſwade them, what an eaſie thing it was to rout the Enemy that was ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and that had not any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their Approach; and that unleſs they did ſpeedily make uſe of the Opportunity, the Horſe and Baggage would be delivered into the Hands of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> whoſe Numbers were able to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ſmall Party that came di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly that way. It was too late to go back, we were now ſo near, that unleſs we did ſurprize the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, it was impoſſible to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape.</p>
            <p>According to our Generals Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <pb n="99" facs="tcp:104773:54"/> as it began to dawn, we march'd with all ſpeed into the Plain along the River, and about two or three hours in the night we came within the Noiſe of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Tents.</p>
            <p>Our General divided us into three Parties, appointing over each a skilful Leader, an <hi>Acha Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha,</hi> and commanded that we ſhould fall upon the <hi>Arabs</hi> in three places.</p>
            <p>Out of the Main Body he had ſeparated a certain number to ſeiſe on certain ſtragling Horſes which might be feeding about the Camp; Theſe he intended to employ in caſe he put the Army to flight.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as we came within a quarter of a Mile of the Enemy, we found a ſmall Party lodged in a hundred Tents, which we ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded according to our Orders. We killed all that we found alive,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104773:55"/> with very little noiſe. In the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and by the Bank of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver great Companies of Horſes were taken for our uſe.</p>
            <p>It ſeems theſe Tents had been placed to guard them from Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers or Wild Beaſts: Our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral made very good uſe of them in the Diſorder and Confuſion of the Rebels, for he cauſed them to be mounted by ſome of his own Party, and commanded them to purſue the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as we came to the firſt Tents, we fell upon them without Mercy, and did great Execution. The two other Parties entred the Camp by ſeveral ways, having fetch'd a Compaſs about; we found no reſiſtance until we came to the middle of the Tents.</p>
            <p>There was a large Spot of Ground unto which the <hi>Arabs</hi> did run together at the ſound of the <pb n="101" facs="tcp:104773:55"/> Alarm: They had not time to put themſelves in a good Order; therefore at the third Volley of Shot they began to diſperſe, and to ſhift for themſelves by divers ways. The two other Parties met ſeveral Companies of them, which they either kill'd or took Priſoners. The moſt of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered their Horſes, and fled for their Lives.</p>
            <p>Our ſmall Party of Horſe was not idle in the mean whiles; they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd after the Enemy with more Noiſe, than Ability to do harm.</p>
            <p>In the dark their Numbers could not be well diſcerned; but this hindred them from viewing us the next day; for knowing that we had both Horſe and Foot, they would not hazard themſelves near us, until they had been informed by ſome Runaways of our ſmall Numbers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:104773:56"/>They fled to the next Hills, where all their Subſtance had been ſtored.</p>
            <p>The Plunder of the Camp was but ſmall; ſuch things we found that Beggars would ſcarce lift from under their Feet; a few naſty Tents we erected of ſuch pitiful Stuff that I never ſaw the like. It ſeems the
<hi>Arabs</hi> delight not in rich Houſhold-ſtuff, but in numbers of Sheep and Camels.</p>
            <p>Some few Horſes fell into our hands the next day.</p>
            <p>In this Attempt we loſt about 50 men, and 435 of the
<hi>Arabians</hi> were kill'd in and about the Camp. Our General found in ſome of the Tents Letters ſent from the <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in the other Kingdoms, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage theſe to reſiſt the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power, promiſing all aſſiſtance that they could furniſh: For fear there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Enemy ſhould receive <pb n="103" facs="tcp:104773:56"/> from their Neighbours and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſuch Supplies as ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and for fear we ſhould loſe the paſſage of the River, which was of ſo great importance to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Affairs and Deſigns, our General and his Council reſolved to fortifie themſelves on both ſides in the beſt manner that the place would permit; and with all ſpeed to diſpatch away ſome Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to the other Armies, to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten them in their March to his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; for he knew himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to encounter the
<hi>Arabs,</hi> or to proceed in his Deſigns and March towards
<hi>Chinſan</hi> with his ſmall Number.</p>
            <p>Three Trenches were drawn on the Enemies ſide, and one on the other. There we thought our ſelves ſecure; for the Enemies Horſe were not able to come to us, <pb n="104" facs="tcp:104773:57"/> their Foot were poor and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ten of them do not dare to look a <hi>Turk</hi> in the Face.</p>
            <p>The ſituation of the Place did favour our Enterprize; for the Ground on both ſides is higher than the reſt at the Ford. The River is deep in all other places, and runs in a narrow Channel; but when it comes there, it ſpreads it ſelf, finding more Elbow room: The Riſing Ground forces it to run in a larger Stream, and then again the Water is confin'd to a leſſer Channel; ſo that only in this place we may paſs on foot without fear of Drowning.</p>
            <p>Two days after the Battel, our Cavalry and Baggage came ſafe to us, although they had been met by ſeveral Parties of <hi>Arabs,</hi> and forced to skirmiſh many times.</p>
            <p>By this new Supply our Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages began to encreaſe; we were
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:104773:57"/> better able to reſiſt our Enemies Attempts in caſe they ſhould be ſo bold as to force our weak Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</p>
            <p>We lay not long in this Poſture, before we ſaw many reſolute Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Horſe and Foot daring us out to Battel. They began to contemn thoſe that they formerly feared, when they knew our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: Every Night we had two or three Alarms given unto us.</p>
            <p>The ſecond day after the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of our Cavalry, a ſtrong Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Horſe rid within Musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of us, calling us Cowards and Hereticks. Our Generals Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage could not ſuffer long theſe ſmall Affronts unpuniſhed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he commanded the Cavalry to haſten out and to charge them ſtoutly. It was a ſad Enterprize to many of them; above a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand went out, but ſcarce five <pb n="106" facs="tcp:104773:58"/> hundred came back again. The cauſe of their Defeat was this; At the firſt Charge the Enemy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats in good Order; but when the <hi>Turks</hi> gave another Onſet, they ran away, only with a Deſign to draw us by that feigned flight far from the Main Body, and into a ſtrong Ambuſcado that was hid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind a Hill about a Mile from the River: Our men perceived not the Deſign, but with more haſte than good ſpeed purſued them without conſideration of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as they were paſt the place, a good Company of Foot ſalutes them with a Volley of ſhot on the left hand, and then the Ambuſcado of Horſe riſes on the Right, at the ſame time the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Party turns their backs, and our poor men were ſurrounded, diſordered, and killed like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <pb n="107" facs="tcp:104773:58"/> Sheep: Had they not had a ſtout Commander to lead them on and bring them off, they had all periſhed in the place; for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Numbers of the Enemy did overpower them. About 500 eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped from the Slaughter.</p>
            <p>This Misfortune did wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully heighten the Courage of the
<hi>Arabians,</hi> and give Credit to their Arms.</p>
            <p>It made our General more wary for the future, and prevented greater Deſtructions which might have happened unto us, had we not been made wiſer by our Loſſes.</p>
            <p>The Enemy at ſeveral other times did endeavour again to catch us in the ſame Advantage; but our General was grown wary by Experience.</p>
            <p>That the Spirits of his men might not be dejected, nor the
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs</hi> 
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:104773:59"/> too proud of their Succeſs, he drew out both Horſe and Foot, and put them in a readineſs to fight.</p>
            <p>The Enemy came to look upon us; our Horſe was ſent to take a view of them: They returned again after a light Skirmiſh, in which the Rebels had the worſt. Every day we did encounter with them, ſometimes to our Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſometimes to our Loſs. We lay not long in this place before we heard of the approach of the Eaſtern Army, Commanded by the two Generals. They had not met with any oppoſition in their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, until they came within a days Journey of us; then a ſtrong Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Horſe oppoſes them, and forces them to ſeek the ſhelter of a Hill, where they were better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to receive the Onſet of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians.</hi> It ſeems they had heard
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:104773:59"/> of the March of that Army to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, therefore to prevent our joining together, or rather to defeat them before they came up with us, a great number of them had ſtollen over the River ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at a great diſtance from us, and had expected them in their way.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as this News came to our Camp, our General reſolved to meet them in perſon, leaving in the Fortifications a ſufficient num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to defend it, and the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of his being preſent. It was my Maſters and my Fortune to accompany the Army.</p>
            <p>At a place called by the <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Stefee,</hi> we came up with the Enemy: A Party of Horſe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged us very ſtoutly with Lance &amp; Musket: Not many of ours were wounded, only four or five killed. They met with as ſtout reſiſtance, which forced them from us, not <pb n="110" facs="tcp:104773:60"/> without loſs. Our Horſe had the Chaſe of them a Mile. We did not dare to adventure again after them farther; beſides, they were more nimble than ours, becauſe they had not been tired with ſo long a Journey.</p>
            <p>By this ſmall Encounter and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory we opened a way to our men that we found in no ſmall diſtreſs for want of Proviſions and things neceſſary.</p>
            <p>They could not proceed in their Journey for fear of the Enemy, that had had great advantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them.</p>
            <p>We found them entrenched in a ſtrong place, in ſuch a manner that all the <hi>Arabians</hi> were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to drive them from thence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were by Famine. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed us of what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; that the <hi>Arabians</hi> had beaten them twice, and kill'd
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:104773:60"/> above a Thouſand Men. The firſt time they laid an Ambuſcado in their way, near a thick Wood, and when ſome Companies were paſt the place they fell ſuddainly upon them without mercy, and had not the Generals expoſed their Perſons to the Peril, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Fight with the Victorious Enemy, until the others had ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed again, they had been all ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt; for they were in ſuch a diſorder, that they killed one another to make way for to fly.</p>
            <p>Our Men were poſſeſt with ſo ſtrange a fear and apprehenſion, that when our Vanguard came near the place, they imagined them to be the Enemy; their joy was no leſs than their fear, when they perceived their errour. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us as their Protectors. We ſupplyed them with all things that they wanted, and then Marched <pb n="112" facs="tcp:104773:61"/> back again to our Camp, unto which the other Army ſoon arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>With this recruit it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved we ſhould ſtay no longer there, but beat up the Quarters of the Enemy: Accordingly the next day we Marched out Bag and Baggage, having left a ſmall Guard in the place to keep it, to ſecure our paſſage over again, in caſe we ſhould meet with the Misfortunes of War, which might oblige us to a Retreat.</p>
            <p>At two Miles diſtance from the River, a ſmall Party had the Courage to Charge us, but they would not ſtand to it long. We Marched up the Hill with a great deal of Courage and Reſolution: Our men were ſo enraged by their former Loſſes, that they would not pardon any of the Enemy that fell by chance into their hands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:104773:61"/>This Mountain is called <hi>Houlah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ka;</hi> it is about ten miles round; it reaches very high; about it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Cottages are built, that ſerve for habitation to the Natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Country, the <hi>Moors;</hi> they are poor and needy for the moſt part, they feed upon ſuch things as grow wild in the Valley; for although this Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain appears entire to the Behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers afar off, with a continued Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, there are many Valleys in it, and it is compoſed of ſeveral little Hills: The lower ground is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream fruitful, watered with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pleaſant Fountains that poure down their ſtreams towards the River <hi>Tapna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This place is adorned with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goodly Trees and Woods, which as in moſt places grow na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally without planting, in that ground which hath not been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="114" facs="tcp:104773:62"/> employed, whereof there is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in the Land.</p>
            <p>The Earth of it ſelf abhors Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; when therefore it is neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by reaſon of the ſmall Number of Inhabitants, or when it hath been long without employing its innate productive virtue, it then breaks forth into Trees &amp; Wood, as in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> is ſufficiently known: Our Plantations have been forc'd to make way for their Habitations with the Axe and the Saw, to hew down the Wood that did cover the Countrey; and in our Iſland, as ſome ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters tell us, <hi>Cumberland</hi> and
<hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland,</hi> and all the Northern Parts of <hi>England</hi> were full of Woods, Trees and Buſhes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon the Mountains, where ſcarce any Wood is now to be ſeen.</p>
            <p>In this place the <hi>Arabians</hi> did <pb n="115" facs="tcp:104773:62"/> think to find a ſafe Retreat; and the rather, becauſe there were not many Advenues to the Top: Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had on all ſides fenced it, and diſtinguiſhed it from the other Land by high and ſteepy Rocks. Five Paſſages do lead into this Place; the largeſt is a way about a hundred feet broad, in moſt places covered on both ſides with Sandy Hills, Woods and Rocks that ſeem to threaten the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>The Entrance into this Place was ſomewhat terrible unto us, not only becauſe of the nature of the Situation, but alſo becauſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy had ſeized upon all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult places and paſſages to annoy us.</p>
            <p>Our Generals were reſolved to beat them from thence, and to fight them in their Neſt.</p>
            <p>Both ſides of the way were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <pb n="116" facs="tcp:104773:63"/> with Armed men, that did caſt upon us Stones, Timber, and whatſoever they could get. We defended our ſelves with Offenſive and Defenſive Weapons, and made a way by the Sword, until we came to a very difficult Paſſage: On both ſides were raiſed two Buſhy Woods, in which the Enemy were hid; when our men came near, they let fly againſt us ſeveral Volleys of Shot, which put us all to ſtand. The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> thought us to be amazed at this ſudden oppoſition, of which they intended to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, in an inſtant came thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring upon us before and behind, the ſtouteſt of them; ſo that we were in no little trouble how to oppoſe them. Our Generals ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongſt themſelves the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the honour of the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; they ſeeing the craft and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <pb n="117" facs="tcp:104773:63"/> of the
<hi>Arabians,</hi> ſeparated themſelves, and turned their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies againſt the next Troops of the Enemy, and did ſo handſomly behave themſelves, and ſo wiſely manage their buſineſs, that the
<hi>Arabians</hi> were forced to leave us the Maſters of the Field, with the Victory. One thing did very much contribute to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of it; not far from that place an eaſie Aſcent did lead to the other ſide of one of the woods, where the <hi>Arabians</hi> had ſecured themſelves: By this, one of our Generals ſteals up, and falls upon the back of the Enemy, that thought next upon nothing but how to ſave themſelves by flight. Our men purſued their advantage, and left not their buſineſs half fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; they ſeized upon the place, and drove the <hi>Arabians</hi> quite out of the Wood with great <pb n="118" facs="tcp:104773:64"/> ſlaughter. Their Fellows ſeeing their diſorder, and the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Men, that would not retire back, imagined ſome ſuch thing might happen on their ſide, therefore they all ran away; ſo ſtrange a paſſion is Fear, that when Men are inclinable to it, the leaſt accident cauſeth them to tremble; all the World would not have been able to have beat them from this place, had they maintained it with reſolution; but the ſight of an Enemy behind, which they leaſt ſuſpected, frighted them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. They recovered the other ſide, where their Horſes ſtayed for them, and ſo ſaved themſelves from the
<hi>Turks</hi> Fury. They loſt here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1500 Men. in the Valleys we found many hundred Head of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, Sheep, Oxen, Cammels, and all ſorts of Beaſts, feeding in the Paſtures: It was wonderful to us
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:104773:64"/> to meet with ſuch a fruitful place in the midſt of ſo many Rocks and ſuch barren Hills. For all theſe Loſſes the
<hi>Arabians</hi> would not return to their former Obedience, but continued ſtill to reſiſt us: Our Camp did receive ſeveral A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms, eſpecially in the Night, ſo that we were all tired out with Watching.</p>
            <p>Above three Weeks we were purſuing the Enemy amongſt the Hills, from one Hill to another: They did fly continually, and becauſe we were not ſo ſtrong in Cavalry as they were, we did not dare to adventure againſt them, only with our Horſe; our Foot were not able to purſue them ſo faſt as they did ſave themſelves: The Plunder that we did find in theſe places, did abundantly ſatisfie for the yearly Tribute. The great numbers of Cattel that we got <pb n="120" facs="tcp:104773:65"/> into our hands, cauſed the <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to fall out amongſt themſelves; which coming to our Ears, our Generals ſent a Flag of Truce, to invite them to ſubmit to the
<hi>Turks</hi> Empire; a part of them accepted the offer of Peace, and came in to us; the others with their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was ſaid to have fled away, ſo that meeting with none to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us, we received ſome Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges from the Enemy; and becauſe their Loſſes had been great, our Generals would not exact from them any other Tribute, than what they had recovered by force of Arms. They had full liberty to return to their former abode, upon condition that they would Manure the Ground, and pay unto them of <hi>Argiers</hi> their uſual Tribute-money; they promiſed to be alwaies obedient to the Grand Seignior, and to the City <pb n="121" facs="tcp:104773:65"/> of <hi>Argeirs;</hi> afterwards they were diſmiſt: There were about 1600 Families that did return to their Duty with all their Leaders.</p>
            <p>Our Army took another way out of theſe Mountains than we came. No Enemy appear'd all the way, until we came to a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row paſſage between two high Hills; the way was a difficult Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: Here we found it ſtopt up in ſuch a manner that no Horſe could paſs. Before we imagined our buſineſs had been done, when we ſaw ſo many of the revolted
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> return to their Obedience; it did not therefore a little ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize us, when we found ſo many left to oppoſe us at this Paſſage, it was not poſſible for us to come near: Several of our Companies did endeavour to ſtorm the place, but the Enemy was ſo ſtrongly fortified on all ſides, and ſo well <pb n="122" facs="tcp:104773:66"/> furniſhed with Weapons, that we were forced to ſit down and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what to do: A Council was called of all the Commanders, where it was reſolved not to go back or ſeek any other paſſage, becauſe if they did leave ſuch a powerful Enemy unpuniſhed, and on foot in the heart of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, it might very much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger their intereſt there; for aſſoon as they ſhould be gone, they would endeavour to corrupt the reſt, and draw them from their Allegiance, either by force or fair means; beſides, they did conſider that they that had ſubmitted unto them, were forced unto it, and that they were as inclinable to ſtand out as theſe, were there any hopes of proſpering in their oppoſition againſt us; and that it would be no ſmall Diſgrace to a victorious Army to be overcome by a van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd <pb n="123" facs="tcp:104773:66"/> Enemy: the leaſt News of this would be able to encourage the reſt of the
<hi>Turks</hi> Subjects to revolt: For theſe and many other Reaſons they thought it neceſſary to make way through that place and no other. The difficulty was to find out the means of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Deſign: By plain force they did ſee it impoſſible.</p>
            <p>We had given ſeveral Attempts to no other purpoſe but to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage our men with the loſs of their Companions. My Maſter was wounded with a Stone caſt from a Sling. It Seems ſome of theſe
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> are excellent Marks-men, and very dexterous at this old kind of Weapon.</p>
            <p>There was no other way to come to fight with theſe People but one, which was alſo ſo well fortified, that we loſt our Labour and Men to attempt it. Our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals <pb n="124" facs="tcp:104773:67"/> were afraid that this ſmall Party that held out againſt us, would encreaſe by degrees, if they did once oblige us to a ſtand, and that they would leſſen the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of our Men in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, if we could not overcome them.</p>
            <p>Firſt they reſolved to ſend a Flag of Truce, to try whether they could win them to a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able complyance without Arms: The
<hi>Arabians</hi> were glad to ſee this expreſſion of our Weakneſs, which they might have improved to their advantage, had they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the Offers that would have been made. They had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived again at their own terms, but as people that relie upon their own ſtrength, they took this as an open acknowledgment of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of our paſſage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their leave, and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <pb n="125" facs="tcp:104773:67"/> ſufficiently ſecure againſt all our Attempts; therefore when our Meſſenger came with Offers of Peace, they were ready to beat him, and would not read the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent to their General, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly, before him, trod it under feet, telling him, that they knew our Demands without read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Letter, and that they would ſpeedily return an Anſwer in the Company of Thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men. This unexpected Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Civility of our Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did not a little trouble them; for they imagined that ſo proud and confident an Anſwer did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſome powerful aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance expected by the Enemy from their Brethren of the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Provinces: Their Conjecture was not in vain; for they had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received the promiſes of a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſupply from them of <hi>Fez, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gad,</hi> 
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:104773:68"/> and <hi>Snatta,</hi> three Provinces, very large, where ſeveral of the Tribes of the <hi>Arabians</hi> do inhabit with the ancient Natives the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricans,</hi> the one in Tents, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſmall Villages. They were upon their March when they heard of the firſt Defeat that the <hi>Turks</hi> had given to their Brethren at the difficult paſſage. Fame had encreas'd the Number of the ſlain, and repreſented the ſlaughter to them ten times worſe than really it was.</p>
            <p>Some time before they had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd a Meſſenger with News of their coming, which Meſſenger did according to his Orders, give an Account of the Numbers and Reſolution of them that ſent him to the Beſieged. They relied up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his words, not knowing of the contrary intentions that the change of Affairs had produced <pb n="127" facs="tcp:104773:68"/> in them; for aſſoon as they heard of the <hi>Turks</hi> Succeſſes, and their own Misfortunes, they returned back again, leaving their Friends and Brethren to our Mercy, and their own Protection.</p>
            <p>This we knew not when the Meſſenger returned with ſuch a reſolute Anſwer: Therefore our Leaders thought it their Intereſt, to overcome the Enemy before any Supply might come to them.</p>
            <p>We lay ſeveral days not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what courſe to take, until the <hi>Arabians</hi> themſelves furniſhed us an occaſion to overcome them: They ſent out about Fifty Men to ſteal Cattel, theſe we trapand &amp; took every one of them: Aſſoon as news came to our General of their ſurpriſal, he commands 50 choice Men to be pickt out of the Army, ſome of them ſpoke the <hi>Arabian</hi> Tongue well, ſo that they
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:104773:69"/> could not be diſtinguiſhed, theſe he cauſes to be habited as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> were, and to be armed with four Piſtols a piece, which were hid in their Boſoms; then he gives them about an hundred Head of Cattel to drive before them towards the <hi>Arabians:</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſufficiently inſtructed them what to do, and informed them of the ſignal to be given, in caſe they did ſucceed, he Commands them to March.</p>
            <p>They accordingly aſcend up to the narrow Paſſage, where the Enemy kept a ſtrong Guard, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as they came within Call, they were ordered to pronounce <hi>Mahummed i ſhur,</hi> the Word that was given the Thieves, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from others; at that the Paſſage was opened, and they drove in the Beaſts without any oppoſition; the Purchaſe did not <pb n="129" facs="tcp:104773:69"/> a little pleaſe our Enemies, becauſe they had been put to ſome ſtraits for want of Victuals; they had ſome a coming from the other ſide, but it was not yet arrived; but when the Drivers of theſe Cattel proved to be none of their Friends, their joy was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fear.</p>
            <p>Our Men were no ſooner enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but they left the Conduct of the Beaſts to ſome other Body, and fell to their work; they kill'd and ſurpriſed all the Guards there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, and poſſeſſed themſelves of the Advenue, giving notice thereof by a ſudden flaſh of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently aſcended the Hill and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the place; had they not arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in time, all our Men had been cut to pieces, for they were mightily oppreſſed with numbers, but we came opportunely to their
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:104773:70"/> aſſiſtance, and forced the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> to ſeek ſafety in their heels.</p>
            <p>Our Army paſſed into the Plain Countrey again, in purſuance of their Enemies, who being tired with ſo many Misfortunes and Loſſes, and ſeeing none come to their aſſiſtance, they ſent ſome of their chief Men to treat with us about Peace; their Meſſage was acceptable to the whole Army.</p>
            <p>That which moſt perſwaded them to ſubmit unto the
<hi>Turks,</hi> was, becauſe many of them had left their Wives and Children in the laſt Engagement behind them, to the <hi>Turks</hi> diſpoſition. Their Captivity did highly concern their near Relations, therefore they ſought all means to recover them again by a firm Treaty. They excuſed unto us the impertinent Anſwer, and the great Contempt of the <hi>Turks</hi> firſt Offers, upon a <pb n="131" facs="tcp:104773:70"/> certain number of them that were then amongſt the dead, aſſuring us that thoſe that were alive, had been led into this Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Wills, by meer neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe they had a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon the Chief Men of them that were kill'd: For they have ſeveral ſtrong Factions amongſt them, the chief Diſpoſers of all the reſt, according to his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; they ſwear by
<hi>Mahomet</hi> to maintain and follow him whither ſoever he goes.</p>
            <p>Our Generals received them into Favour again, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that every Year they ſhould pay a double Tribute, as a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to their Rebellion. <hi>Elm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwar Tapnez</hi> their Chief Captain fled with all ſpeed towards <hi>Angad,</hi> that lies full South of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of
<hi>Argiers,</hi> ſo that he could never come into the <hi>Turks</hi> power.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:104773:71"/> We diſmiſt thoſe that yielded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and returned them their Wives and Children.</p>
            <p>Our Generals having ſo happily made an end of this War, that threatened the <hi>Turks</hi> Intereſt in thoſe Parts, began to ſeparate again, and to proceed in their Journey over the Kingdom, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Tribute-money.</p>
            <p>The People pay by the Head two Dollars, that is nine Shillings a Head, Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; thoſe that are very rich in Cattel are forced to part with more, when the Army goes the Rounds; and if any is extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary poor in a Family, his Neighbours and near Kinsfolks muſt ſupply his wants, and pay for him; ſo that the total Sum of this Tribute is very great, I have heard ſome ſpeak of ten Millions of Dollars, beſides the Expences
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:104773:71"/> of the Army. This Money is brought into <hi>Argiers,</hi> ſome part of it is ſent to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the Grand Segnior, another part defrays the Expences of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia and Officers of Church and State, and another part is caſt into the Publick Treaſury.</p>
            <p>Our Army proceeded right to <hi>Chinſan</hi> or
<hi>Tremiſen,</hi> a ſtrong and populous City, kept by the <hi>Turks</hi> with a numerous Guard that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved every year. Our General was deſigned Governour of this place, and was ſent thither with his Army to Command it.</p>
            <p>We had a very pleaſant Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from this Mountain to that City, thorough a fruitful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that did furniſh us both with Money and good Entertainment; ſome of them had been in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, but the
<hi>Turks</hi> would not deal with them more ſeverely than
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:104773:72"/> with the others, to oblige them to a greater Fidelity; for their is no greater tye to Obedience than Love, and the ſenſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Obligations: Our Army might have treated them as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſold their Goods, taken their Wives and diſpoſed of them as Bond-ſlaves; but they knew that this dealing would ſerve to no other purpoſe, but to exaſperate the Spirits of the reſt, who might then have reaſon to ſeek an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Revenge. It is never good to deal with Men as with Beaſts; the latter are awed into obedience, but the firſt muſt be perſwaded: The Magiſtrates ſword may ſcare me, but it ſhall never win me.</p>
            <p>This Practice of the <hi>Turks</hi> was very commendable: They thought it unworthy their Courage to tread on the Neck of a vanquiſh'd
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:104773:72"/> and yielding Enemy. Our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to oblige the Chief of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Tribes, did invite ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them to eat with him; he beſtowed Gifts upon ſome of the Arch Rebels, imitating the practiſe of thoſe Princes that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow their Favours upon thoſe that are ſuſpected, or that have been rebellious, to oblige them to be more faithful to their Intereſt for the future.</p>
            <p>At a ſmall Town, called by the <hi>Turks, Canatudi,</hi> and by the <hi>Moors, Canahaal,</hi> there was a great Feaſt kept for the Marriage of one <hi>Elmſwar Bidow Ben hemmed,</hi> an <hi>Alcalde</hi> of one of their Tribes; our General coming to the place at that time, honoured the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with his preſence, and cauſed all his Captains and <hi>Chouſes</hi> to pay their reſpects to the Bride and Bridegroom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:104773:73"/>I cannot paſs further until I take notice of what is obſerved by this People in ſuch occaſions; the young man that hath a mind to marry, demands the Daughter from her Father, or next Kindred; if they grant her, he never trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelf to win her conſent; this is an excellent way to ſpare a great deal of hypocriſie, and to ſave the poor men much Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: The man makes a great Feaſt according to his Quality; ſome do treat their Friends ſeven days; the firſt day he ſends to his future Spouſe by ſome Kinſwoman, a Vail, to recommend unto her Modeſty; the ſecond day, a Suit of Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, ſuch as they wear; the third day, a Mill to grind Corn, and Inſtruments to ſpin, to remember ſhe may not be idle; the fourth, an <hi>Alcoran;</hi> the fifth, a pair of Slippers handſomly made and <pb n="137" facs="tcp:104773:73"/> guilded; the ſixth day he ſends a Cock and a Dog, to teach her Diligence and Watchfulneſs; and the ſeventh, a Ring of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Faſhion, with a Diſh of Meat, and a Staff with this Motto about it, <hi>I will puniſh all Offenders.</hi> All this while the Bridegroom hath not ſo much as ſeen his future Spouſe, but ſends to viſit her often with ſome courſe Complements, as as is uſual amongſt
<hi>Moors.</hi> On the eighth day, which is that of the greateſt Solemnity, the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom comes to the Fathers houſe, accompanied by all his Friends and Kindred, and there in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them all, the Father de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers all his right, title and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in his Daughter, to the man, by giving unto him her hand, and ſaying ſome words proper to the buſineſs in hand. They go next to the place of Prayer, which in <pb n="138" facs="tcp:104773:74"/> Tents is near the middle; and there a <hi>Thaloub</hi> bleſſeth the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Couple, adding ſeveral Prayers to God, and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and to the Angel
<hi>Zadiel,</hi> that governs, as they ſay, the Planet <hi>Jupiter,</hi> to favour this Conjunction by ſome happy influence. Then they all march in order to the Fathers Houſe, where a great Feaſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them: The men by themſelves in one Room make merry; the Women in another, are jolly until the Evening: Then the Bride in all her State, with all her Houſhold-ſtuffe, Servants, Gifts and Money, is carried to the mans Houſe; ſhe uſually ſits mounted on a Camel, glittering in Gold and Silk, and about her are all her Kindred and Friends. When ſhe comes to her Husbands Houſe, ſhe then pulls off her Vail, becauſe Modeſty is no longer in <pb n="139" facs="tcp:104773:74"/> ſeaſon, nor proper to that place. Some do keep ſeveral Feaſt days afterwards, and ſpend much of their Eſtate, according to their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, or the love they bear to the Spouſe.</p>
            <p>I was an Eye-witneſs of ſeveral Ceremonies obſerved in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which are related in other Travels.</p>
            <p>We ſtayed in this place ſeveral days to refreſh our ſelves, and then we continued our Journey towards <hi>Chinſan,</hi> where we arrived on the third of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a large and populous City, inhabited by a kind of People called <hi>Lhebdiah;</hi> round about are moſt pleaſant Gardens and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards. The Soil is good, the Climate wants nothing but People worthy to receive and enjoy the good things that it affords.</p>
            <p>We found here great ſtore of <pb n="140" facs="tcp:104773:75"/> Fruits, Apples, Pears, Melons of divers kinds, Grapes; for although the
<hi>Mahumetan</hi> drinks not Wine, he loves the Grape, and a kind of Drink that is made of Water and Raiſins, called <hi>Africana;</hi> it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant, and proper for this Climate.</p>
            <p>Here is a ſtrange ſort of Tree made up of Leaves, one Leaf grows on the top of another; the Leaves are thick two or three inches in the middle; they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a foot large and long; an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Fruit grows upon them, which the <hi>Arabs</hi> call <hi>Aſholoch,</hi> our <hi>Engliſh, Prickle Pear;</hi> the Subſtance is cold and refreſhing; it is ripe about
<hi>Midſummer,</hi> and of a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſh colour. Every Garden is furniſhed with ſuch a Tree: The Rind is full of little Prickles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcernable; therefore it is not to be handled with naked hands. I <pb n="141" facs="tcp:104773:75"/> have ſince ſeen ſome in other parts.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo a beautiful Tree of divers Colours, that the Great Men cauſe to grow in the midſt of their Gardens; it ſerves as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ornament to a place: Its Body is of a deep green, the Boughs red, the Leaves yellow as Gold, with a mixture of white. Some told me that this Tree could not grow in any other Climate or Soil, and that ſome had laboured to tranſplant it on the Sea-ſhore, but that Air had rendred all their Labours and Endeavours to little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Here is great abundance of Dates: That Tree never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces unleſs there be a Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Male with the Female; they uſually join their Boughs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>I had time in this place to take <pb n="142" facs="tcp:104773:76"/> a view of all the Rarities: It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me to be one of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt Cities of the World; it ſtands upon a plain ground, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a ſtrong Wall, beautified with many ſquare Marble Pillars, very white, the reſt of the Wall being built of a brown ſtone; on the top the Bulwarks are adorned with Turrets of divers colours. The City yields a pleaſant ſight to the Beholder when the Sun ſhines. The inſide is no leſs beautiful. The Streets are ſtraight and broad. The Heart of the City contains many excellent Buildings. A ſtately <hi>Moſque</hi> ſupported by a hundred Pillars of white Marble, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Arches of very curious work; the Governours Palace, where there are a hundred large Rooms very neatly adorned with ſeveral miſhapen Figures of divers Colours; for the <hi>Mahumetans</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor <pb n="143" facs="tcp:104773:76"/> Images and Statues; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have not the uſe of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, nor do not allow them to appear publickly in any place.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo a Town-Houſe, a place appointed for the meeting of the Chief Perſons when any urgent Buſineſs calls them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult together: It ſtands upon an Arch ſupported by two Rows of Marble Pillars. It hath a Steeple to it built with half Brick and half Stone, very high and large. The top hath a Proſpect into all the Countrey as far as our Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight will reach; and in one ſide is a large Room full of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Records of the <hi>Arabians</hi> ſince the firſt Conqueſt of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, with many Large Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes.</p>
            <p>The next Place to it is the Court that belongs to the
<hi>Cadir,</hi> the Chief Juſtice, where he ſits upon <pb n="144" facs="tcp:104773:77"/> a Seat covered with a Canopy of Cloth of Silver, the Seat is eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above the reſt in the manner of a Table ſpred with <hi>Turky</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, upon which he ſits as a Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. A Fellow ſtands at his El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow with a naked Cymeter; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him a little lower, ſit ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Aſſiſtants, whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel he takes in difficult Affairs. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver againſt ſtands the Parties to be judged without delay; they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally receive the Puniſhments due to their Offence, at the ſame time that they are judged; for they admit of no Reprieve.</p>
            <p>There are many other Houſes very well built; they are flat on the Top; ſome are curiouſly painted according to the <hi>Moſaique</hi> Faſhion. The Inhabitants do ſleep upon them in the Summer, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an
<hi>Alhage,</hi> to defend them from the venomous Flies, and from
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:104773:77"/> the <hi>Musketa's,</hi> pernicious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſuck their Blood.</p>
            <p>In the middle of the City is a large Market-place, and round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout many Cloiſters of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men amongſt the <hi>Moors.</hi> One is more remarkable than the reſt, becauſe of the excellent Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip and ancient Fabrick, and becauſe of a great Library, a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thing amongſt this rude Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: I know not with what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Books it is ſtored; for Chriſtians have never the liberty to handle them; but as I did learn from the Keepers of the Door, they were Books that had been pick'd up in all the parts of <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> by one of their Princes, and laid in that place, for the benefit of the Students, whereof there are very few, unleſs it be of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, and men that ſtudy the Virtues of Simples. Other Arts
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:104773:78"/> and Sciences, as <hi>Aſtrology, Logick,</hi> the
<hi>Mathematicks,</hi> &amp;c. are almoſt extinct amongſt them.</p>
            <p>In the time of my abode among them, I have perceived that they pretend many times the aſſiſtance of the Devil to work miraculous Effects, when they do it by the Knowledges that they have of Nature.</p>
            <p>They are very ſuperſtitious, and liſten very much to the Reports and Whimſies of their Soothſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>Some never undertake a Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of any Concern, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting theſe Oracles. Many in theſe parts make a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Peoples Folly.</p>
            <p>There is a Society amongſt them that profeſs Fortune-telling. It is not ſo much diſcredited as in our Kingdom: They are perſons for the moſt part of Honour and <pb n="147" facs="tcp:104773:78"/> Reputation that are admitted to a familiar acquaintance with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits. They vouchſafe not to appear and diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to every idle Raſcal. I have ſeen wonderful Cures performed by their means, not ſo much by the ſecret operation of the Spirit, as by the virtue of Herbs and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines applied to the Patient, which were directed and reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Evil Spirit; for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is a good Phyſitian, he may diſpute the Palm with
<hi>Hypocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi> I have ſeen a deaf man, whoſe Organ was only obſtructed, and not incapacitated, cured by the Application of an Herb like unto our Sorrel, called <hi>Hegn</hi> by the <hi>Moors.</hi> Agues and Fevers are driven away by the touch of ſome of theſe Magicians; other Diſeaſes require a longer time, and other Remedies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:104773:79"/>This City is full of this ſort of People that openly acknowledge themſelves to be ſuch, and own a familiarity with ſeveral infernal Spirits: Their Names and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance I could never know from them. I was very inquiſitive to underſtand ſomething of their art; but their Grandeur could not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to entertain a Diſcourſe with a poor Slave. I have ſeen them make Figures &amp; Images of Clay and Wax, which they put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of their houſes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the two Solſtices, in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctials, and in the full Moon; the reaſon, as I did conceive, was to make them receive ſome quality which the Stars do ſend down at ſuch ſeaſons upon the corporal Bodies.</p>
            <p>There are many ſorts of Trades in this place; but as in moſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Barbary,</hi> they all live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <pb n="149" facs="tcp:104773:79"/> in one Street that are of the ſame Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>At one end of the Town hard by the River <hi>Elouad</hi> that waters the Fields of <hi>Climſan,</hi> is erected a ſtately Caſtle, the Seat of the Lieutenant or Governour of the City: It overlooks the Town, and commands it with a hundred Peeces of Ordnance. Nothing is here remarkable but the Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Buildings and Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>It was firſt erected in the time of the <hi>Vandal</hi> Kings, to keep this Inland Countrey in ſubjection, and eſpecially this great and populous City. It hath been ſince enlarged by the <hi>Saracens.</hi> In the middle ſtands a Pillar full of <hi>Arabick</hi> Letters, written in blew Figures upon black Marble, to ſignifie the memorable actions that have been performed in the time of <hi>Saracen</hi> 
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:104773:80"/> or
<hi>Arabick</hi> Kings. They have reigned in theſe parts many years before
<hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to win <hi>Argiers.</hi> A ſmall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Account of their Names and Actions I ſhall annex in its place.</p>
            <p>This City is the largeſt in the whole Kingdom, which is limited on the North ſide by the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean,</hi> on the Eaſt by
<hi>Tunis,</hi> on the South by <hi>Angad,</hi> another large Kingdom in the Land, and by <hi>Snatta,</hi> Province that hath almoſt nothing but Mountains and Rocks; and on the Weſt it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon the Kingdom of <hi>Fez.</hi> It contains 250 Leagues in length, from the Sea in the Land as far as
<hi>Angad,</hi> and about 160 in breadth, from <hi>Bouſema</hi> to the Cape called by our people <hi>Cap de Bugaremo.</hi> It contains ſeveral Cities well forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the chief are <hi>Argiers</hi> and <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſen,</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:104773:80"/> or <hi>Climſan,</hi> ſo called by the Inhabitans; on the Sea-Coaſt are <hi>Cercelli, Bougia, Gigiari, Masta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, Biſche, Gileto, Guien, Arſeni, Oran,</hi> that belongs to the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> where a Marquiſs commands the Countrey about ten Miles round, with ſeven or eight hundred horſe; <hi>Zereni, Arſebiba, Buazia, Corban,</hi> ſome of theſe are Cities, others but ſmall Towns.</p>
            <p>In the Land are many good Towns and Places of Note; theſe are the chief, <hi>Benibachul, Albori, Tegdeme, Stefe, Canatudi, Medua, Calamou, Lori, Albron, Segmes,</hi> a large Town that gives name to a Province ſo called; <hi>Hagroah, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broehl,</hi> and ſeveral others, whoſe Names are hereafter mentioned: I have reckoned up here above a hundred Villages inhabited by the <hi>Africans,</hi> that are Servants to the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and they are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <pb n="152" facs="tcp:104773:81"/> to the <hi>Turk:</hi> Some of them retain the ancient Language. In the Province of <hi>Snatta</hi> they have a particular Speech, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by any but by themſelves: Some told me that it is the old <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Language; for they that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit theſe Mountains and barren Places, were driven thither by the Wars and Cruelty of the new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, who had ground and room enough without troubling that poor ſort of People; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they always left them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their own without diſturbing them; only they have obliged them to receive the Law of
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet:</hi> That was not difficult to impoſe upon a People that before had ſcarce any Religion; or if they had, it was accompanied with ſo much Ignorance and Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they knew no reaſon to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Religion that appeared <pb n="153" facs="tcp:104773:81"/> round about them, ſo ſucceſsful, and ſo univerſally received.</p>
            <p>In this City of <hi>Climſan</hi> I remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 3 years with my Maſter. At our firſt Arrival our General took poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Government, and of the Caſtle, and the former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour took Charge of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute-Money to be conveyed to <hi>Argiers.</hi> A week after our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſet forwards with his Companies that had been weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Diſeaſes of the laſt Year: His Commiſſion ordered him to meet the Weſtern Army, and both together to return home with their ſums of Money. Our Deſtiny ſtaid us in this City, in which I met with various and ſtrange Adventures. I was
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> times obliged to undertake a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with my Maſter in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: firſt was towards
<hi>Angad,</hi> in which Province is a famous and ancient <pb n="154" facs="tcp:104773:82"/> City called <hi>Bedtua,</hi> not inferiour to <hi>Climſan,</hi> unleſs it be in the largeneſs and excellency of the Buildings.</p>
            <p>The Countrey round about is full of all ſorts of Fruit, and is not ſo hot as one might imagine. I found ſeveral ſorts of Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at a very cheap Rate, which we purchaſe with large Sums, and great labour and hazard. Hides, Hony, Bees-Wax are here in a great abundance.</p>
            <p>We paſt over a Sandy Valley a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half way to <hi>Bedtua,</hi> where we found a great deal of glittering Sand, much like to that of Gold. In the middle is a large Lake, unto which the wild Beaſts and Serpents reſort; above 50 or 60 did threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us when we offered to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>Our Buſineſs in theſe parts was to treat with a great Commander <pb n="155" facs="tcp:104773:82"/> of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> the Prince of this Kingdom, about ſome Buſineſs of Importance to our Garriſon. My Maſter was diſpatch'd as an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador with a conſiderable Guard to defend him from the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of wild Beaſts and Lawleſs Thieves, of which the Mountains are peopled.</p>
            <p>It is needleſs to relate all the Particulars of our Journey, and the manner of our Reception.</p>
            <p>We paſſed through many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Tents. They had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for their Situation the moſt pleaſant Valleys, and fruitful Ground. The firſt day we had a ſharp Encounter with about a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen luſty Lions; they hunted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their prey, and met with death at the end of our Muskets. They could not be kill'd without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſome damage: One of our men was wounded with the Paws <pb n="156" facs="tcp:104773:83"/> of one of theſe Furious Beaſts, that leap'd upon him after that he had been ſtruck through the Belly. The danger of our Companion made us diſpatch him ſooner out of the way. This danger was followed by another more fearful; but we eſcaped out of it as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily.</p>
            <p>The next day we paſſed through a large and Sandy Plain of about ten Leagues long, and four broad, called by the <hi>Moors, Scidduahr;</hi> in it were raiſed ſeveral little Hills moveable with the Wind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween which of neceſſity we were to paſs. We were no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, but a ſtrong Eaſterly Wind raiſes the light Sand, and threatens to bury us alive: It was a fearful thing to us to behold ſo much Earth flying in our faces; the Air was thick with the duſty Sand; in a moment a Hill was removed from <pb n="157" facs="tcp:104773:83"/> one place to another; beſides that we had to encounter with the boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous Wind, our Horſes were half buried in a moment, we could not make a ſtop in this dreadful place for fear of being paſt hopes of returning.</p>
            <p>The reſt of our Journey was far more pleaſant; for it afforded us variety of Objects, not ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto us; beſides, the way was leſs dangerous and leſs trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom.</p>
            <p>In eight days we had a ſight of the Walls of <hi>Bedtua:</hi> We were kindly entertained at the Princes Coſt. He was a Perſon of a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Stature, very ſwarthy, in his Face the Characters of Majeſty did appear, and in his Garb and Attendance thoſe of his Dignity. At our arrival 500 Horſe were ſent out to meet us at ſome diſtance from the City; they came in very <pb n="158" facs="tcp:104773:84"/> good Order, and led us to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment that had been prepared for my Maſter Reception aſſoon as they heard of our Approach. We received here the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many perſons of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as the Prince was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Fields, we were ſent to wait upon him. The Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies obſerved on this Occaſion I took exact notice of. The Princes Guards cloathed with a thin Stuff of a Scarlet Die, with red Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and white Feathers flying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, yielded a moſt pleaſant ſight on both ſides of the way, that were lined with them. At a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient diſtance ſtood the officers, whoſe Garb and Meen did make us take notice of them for Perſons more eminent than the reſt. They were as full of Civility as Honour, when my Maſter paſſed by them;
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:104773:84"/> paying unto him as much Reſpect as an Ambaſſador from the Grand Seignior could expect.</p>
            <p>We paſſed through three large Streets in view of many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that did look upon us from the tops of the Houſes and the Windows: Before us matched two grave Fellows very neatly dreſt; next went my Maſter, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by two <hi>Turks</hi> bearing the Preſents deſigned for the Prince. We were attended by many of his Officers.</p>
            <p>When we came to the Palace, the Guards that were at the Gate obliged us to leave our Sandals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
            <p>It is a very large Houſe, built of Marble and Brick; the white and red Colours do yield a pleaſant ſight: We entred into three Courts very handſomly adorned with curious work; at the firſt my <pb n="160" facs="tcp:104773:85"/> Maſter was complemented by the Princes Secretary, at the ſecond by his Brother, and led into the third, where He Himſelf was ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in State. In the middle of it was erected a great Tent of green Silk; at the four Corners, and on the top were Flags of red Silk, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Arms of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and of the Princes Family very neatly wrought: At the Door my Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was met by the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is bound to pay that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to any that comes in the Name of the Grand Seignior. Some Diſcourſe and kind Expreſſions paſſed between them, which I could not approach to hear; they went next both together, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended three Steps at the further end of the Tent, and ſate upon a large Table, my Maſter at the left hand of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Prince; over their Heads a ſtately Canopy <pb n="161" facs="tcp:104773:85"/> was hung, and round about Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the greateſt Quality ſtood, to honour and encreaſe the Solemnity. My Maſter acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with his Buſineſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and received from him a very favourable Anſwer, with a Promiſe to endevour his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſatisfaftion.</p>
            <p>I ſaw here nothing of that rudeneſs, which our People ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to be in all the Parts of <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca:</hi> The Place, and Attendance of the Prince, had as much of State and Glory, as is uſual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the little Princes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> I found nothing barbarous but their Language, which I could not well underſtand.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Arabs</hi> all about <hi>Africa</hi> are People very polite, and well bred; they have nothing of that baſeneſs and uncivil carriage, which other more remote Nations <pb n="162" facs="tcp:104773:86"/> have: They are imperious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People that they have Conquered, becauſe otherwiſe they could never retain them in ſubjection to their Empire; but to Strangers that come amongſt them, they are affable, hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, courteous, kind, and very liberal: If any harm is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Forreigner, it is not by them, but by the raſcally ſort of People, the ancient Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, that look upon all Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for the <hi>Arabs</hi> ſake as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by Race of
<hi>Black-Mores,</hi> whereof there are here great Multitudes ſubject to the
<hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> My Maſter was about three hours in Conference with the Prince, and we as long waiting at the Door of the Tent; all the time a rough ſort of Muſick plaid, five men with ſeveral ſorts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments made a Conſort of <pb n="163" facs="tcp:104773:86"/> Tunes very harſh to our Engliſt Ears.</p>
            <p>When the Diſcourſe was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, my Maſter was led to the Door of the Tent by the Prince, and then by his Grandees he was conduced back to his Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with much Pomp and Joy.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed, I muſt give a further Account of the Prince that Commands ſo far in the Land; his Name is <hi>Moyſes Zim Kuſh,</hi> a man of about forty years of Age, of a middle Stature, not ſo ſwarthy as the ordinary <hi>Moors;</hi> his Body is ſtraight and ſlender, his Face full of Majeſty; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he hath a very loving Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; his people have a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for him: He hath the Command of three great Tribes, that have ſeated themſelves in theſe innermoſt Countries, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sands and Mountains. <pb n="164" facs="tcp:104773:87"/> He had formerly ſome dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon the King of <hi>Fez</hi> and <hi>Morocco;</hi> but now by the death of the laſt Emperour, he became abſolute, as I did then underſtand. And as he commands a great Compaſs of Ground, and hath no little power in regard of the Number of his Men and good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, all his Neighbours have ſometimes need to ſeek his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>My Maſter went not ſo much to Court it as to treat with him about the publick Concerns. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Commodities do grow in his Countrey in a great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, which the Kingdome of <hi>Argeirs</hi> do want: My Maſter had a Commiſſion to procure from him the Liberty of free Trading, and to ſuffer them to be ſent out of his Dominions without ſuch exceſſive Tribute <pb n="165" facs="tcp:104773:87"/> as he did formerly require, to the great prejudice of the <hi>Turks,</hi> that were obliged to buy them for want of others, at any Rate. He had Order alſo to complain of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Violences committed by the Princes Subjects upon the Borders; for ſome few Tents had lately been pitched in the <hi>Turks</hi> Confines by theſe <hi>Arabs,</hi> that would not acknowledge their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and had robbed others that were under their Command, of about a hundred Head of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, under pretence that the Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did ſuffer them to go out of their Limits, and graze where they ſhould not. There were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Robberies done of late by them of
<hi>Angad;</hi> for which my Maſter was to make complaint, and demand reſtitution of the Goods. His buſineſs was alſo to deſire this Prince not to ſuffer his <pb n="166" facs="tcp:104773:88"/> People again to ſend any aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to them of the <hi>Turks</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as they had done of late; and to ſettle a firm Peace and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity between the two Kingdoms of
<hi>Argeirs</hi> and <hi>Angad.</hi> Theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Affairs did require much time and pains to bring to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; for great difficulties did preſent themſelves, that had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt caſt my Maſter into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of accompliſhing his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: The Princes Intereſt did apparently oppoſe it ſelf, and perſwade him not to liſten to the Ambaſſadors Propoſals. His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Word were alſo enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to ſuffer his Brethren to be cruſh'd in pieces without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; and beſides, ſome of the Rebels were fled out of fear, to his Court, where they had made a ſtrong Party to oblige the Prince to favour them and <pb n="167" facs="tcp:104773:88"/> their Concerns, to the prejudice of the <hi>Turk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Difficulties that did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this Negotiation were not to be overcome by an ordinary Judgment and Courage. Four perſons of the
<hi>Sultans</hi> Council were appinted to receive and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Ambaſſadors Propoſals. At firſt they would not liſten to them, but returned a Smile and a Jeſt to his Demands, as if they had been ridiculous: My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did often treat with them, but could not have any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; They anſwered, for the Robberies that were done, they could not be prevented, that the perſons demanded were not be found in thoſe parts; that if any ſuch had done ſuch violences, it was without the Princes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, againſt his Will; and that the perſons were removed far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:104773:89"/> the Countrey, from whence they could not be fetch'd with eaſe: The truth was, that the Prince himſelf had received ſome preſents, and a conſiderable part of the Booty, which he was not willing to let go again. Unto all the other Demands they gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactory Anſwers, which did oblige my Maſter to patience, and a reſolution: Firſt he laboured within a few days to conſider the divers Intereſts that did rule, and the preſent Eſtate of that Court, which did help him on in his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; for he made uſe of thoſe perſons that were able to ſerve him, and did work upon them according to their Inclinations &amp; Intereſts, to put an end to his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation. He had by this wiſe Conduct brought it to a very fair paſs; after much labour and perſwation he had obliged the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:104773:89"/> Prince to a reſtitution of part of the Plunder, and to promiſe to maintain Peace, and not to ſuffer any Injuries to be done by his People to the Subjects of the <hi>Turk.</hi> But this did not ſatisfie my Maſter; he was reſolved to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to conſent to the reſt of his Demands, and to force him to abate ſomething of the great Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms that were raiſed upon the Commodities of the Countrey, that were tranſported out of the Limits; but this could never have been obtained, had it not been for an Accident that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened afterwards; My Maſter was ſo diſcouraged when he came from a Meeting where the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners were preſent, that he gave me order to prepare all things for his ſpeedy departure. I ſaw that his Melancholy look did diſcover his Diſcontent, and <pb n="170" facs="tcp:104773:90"/> his Commands the cauſe of his Diſpleaſure: I made bold with him to comfort him in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and did offer him at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures a remedy to his diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, if he would be pleaſed to tell unto me how his buſineſs did ſtand; he had often tried my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in affairs, and had no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle confidence upon my Fidelity &amp; Wit. This was not the firſt time that I had been uſeful unto him to help him out of difficult Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; therefore he propoſed to me the whole ſtate of his buſineſs. Sir, ſaid I to my Maſter, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not your ſelf, I will cauſe the Prince to give you full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You cannot ſo eaſily do what you have promiſed, replied my Maſter. I anſwered to him, that I was much miſtaken if I had not found out a way to bring him to conſent to things more <pb n="171" facs="tcp:104773:90"/> contrary to his Intereſt than what he had propoſed. He was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know; I told him the Plot, and wiſh'd him to put it ſpeedily in execution; for diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Cauſes require a ſtout reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a great diligence. My Maſter found my Diſcourſe ſo reaſonable, and the Deſign ſo probable, that he began to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace me, and promiſed my free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom his return to <hi>Argiers,</hi> in caſe he ſhould be ſucceſsful in this buſineſs; he proceeded in it as I perſwaded him, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: The Prince of <hi>Angad,</hi> who is honoured with the Title of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> had a Nephew Heir to his Eſtate and Fortune, of a great Courage, and of as great Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; the People had for him a particular reſpect, becauſe his Father had ſacrificed his Life for the publick Good, and becauſe <pb n="172" facs="tcp:104773:91"/> he had an inſinuating preſence, that did command both Love and Reverence from all that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him; he was beſides grown very popular, ſetting his Genius, his Inclinations and Actions to the temper of every one; which Carriage did wonderfully win unto him the eſteem of all the <hi>Arabs;</hi> his Name was <hi>Zidi Hamed Hochbuſh.</hi> Since my Maſters ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in theſe parts, he did often viſit him, and delighted much in his Company: I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had a deſign to ingratiate himſelf by that means with the Garriſon of
<hi>Climſan,</hi> or oblige the <hi>Turks</hi> to his aſſiſtance, in caſe any thing ſhould be undertaken againſt him. My Maſter, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Advice, beſtows upon him at the firſt Interview, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, all the Flatteries &amp; Praiſes that he was able to expreſs, telling
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:104773:91"/> him that ſo noble a Soul was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver born to be a Subject; that the whole Countrey did love him entirely, as one that was worthy of their homages and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; that he would do well to look to himſelf, leſt any Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or Jealouſie, as is uſual in ſuch Occaſions, ſhould ariſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and his Uncle, which might coſt him his Head; that it would become the greatneſs of his Courage and Birth not to ſtoop to ſuch mean Offices as he was employed about; and that that was done purpoſely to abaſe him in the eſteem of the People. This Diſcourſe my Maſter ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſtrong proteſtations of his Love and readineſs to do him Service, promiſing to publiſh his worth among the <hi>Turks</hi> his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen.</p>
            <p>The young man perceived not <pb n="174" facs="tcp:104773:92"/> my Maſters Deſign, but began to conceive very haughty thoughts of himſelf and Abilities.</p>
            <p>Within a few days after he came to pay my Maſter a Viſit. They both entred into an inner Room, admitting none to enter in to them but my ſelf, and there they fell upon the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe: My Maſter omitted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to make him believe that Nature and Providence had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him for the Throne, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as he was Born. As we had before determined to give him a <hi>Regalio,</hi> my Maſter ſent for three Leathern Bottles of Wine, that I had ſecretly conveyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Baggage, and brought to
<hi>Bedtua;</hi> for the <hi>Turks</hi> conſcience may drink Wine privately with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Diſpenſation: The Young-Man had never taſted ſuch a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor in his Daies before, for <pb n="175" facs="tcp:104773:92"/> although they have in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try abundance of Grapes, they have loſt the uſe of Wine: How pleaſing therefore this reception was to him, may be eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
            <p>My Maſter continued in his Hypocriſie, and proteſted, that out of a ſincere reſpect for him, he did offer this rarity to him: The Young-Man was ſoon hot with a little of this Liquor; it made him reveal unto my Maſter ſeveral Intrigues, that were not unuſeful unto him afterwards; but the chiefeſt Operation of this Wine, was, when he met with the Prince his Uncle, who began to chide him for ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent action that he had done, he then fell into ſuch a Paſſion, that all imagined him to be Mad; the Prince caſt a Lance at him, and had he not declined the <pb n="176" facs="tcp:104773:93"/> Blow, he had there ended his daies, and fruſtrated our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>There grew ſuch hatred im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately between them, that they could not ſuffer the ſight of one another: The Prince did not dare to caſt him into Priſon, becauſe of the People; and the Nephew would never truſt him for the future.</p>
            <p>The diſſention was increaſed daily by falſe Friends, who do advantage and pleaſe themſelves with the ruin of others: At laſt, the Young Nephew grew very jealous of his Uncles Deſigns, and began to meditate an Eſcape out of his Dominions: My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter perſwaded him not to delay, but ſpeedily to fly for his Life; for if it were once ſuſpected, his Uncle would not be retained by any conſideration from depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:104773:93"/> him of his Liberty, it may be with his life; for that end he gave him a Horſe, an excellent Courſer that he had brought with him: He made haſte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Borders with a few fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, where he raiſed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that came in to his aſſiſtance; ſo that within a few days he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at the head of 10000 men. News came daily of ſome Parties that did join with them, and at laſt we heard how the <hi>Turks</hi> of
<hi>Argeirs</hi> were reſolv'd to aſſiſt him were not their Demands granted.</p>
            <p>My Maſter began to take his leave aſſoon as this was reported in the Town: The Prince to prevent it, offered him his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and loaded him with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities; for he foreſaw the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conſequence that would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue if he offered to offend the <hi>Turks,</hi> and if they did counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <pb n="178" facs="tcp:104773:94"/> his Nephew in his Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it might prove the ruine of Himſelf and Kingdom; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to engage them to his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which was the moſt juſt, he courted my Maſter, their Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, with all expreſſions of kindneſs; our Lodgings were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways full of Courtiers, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day we did feel and ſee ſome Tokens of the Princes Kindneſs or Fear.</p>
            <p>This part of the Countrey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be in no little apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at firſt; but when my Maſter had received full ſatisfaction, he ſetled their minds with the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that the
<hi>Turks</hi> were too honeſt to approve of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews Rebellion againſt an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle: Yet ſuch was my Maſters kindneſs for the young man, that he mediated for him, and obliged the Prince to invite him again to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:104773:94"/> his Duty, and pardon his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; which he accepted of willingly, when he heard how we had promiſed to lend our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours to his Unkle, in caſe he ſhould remain obſtinate in the purſuance of his wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. He quickly return'd to Court, and was there received with a jealous Countenance, that had always an Eye upon him and his Actions: The fond Love the People had conceived for him ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Life; for none did dare to attempt to injure him that was ſo dear to every one.</p>
            <p>The young mans confidence upon the Peoples Affection made him more impertinent than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he would have been: It made him appear more bold to oppoſe his Unkle, and more negligent in his Duty towards him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:104773:95"/>When we had our Diſpatches, we left him to his own Fortune, and return'd again to <hi>Climſan,</hi> to the great ſatisfaction of all the City, who did hope to reap no ſmall advantage from this Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation. My Maſter had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it, although it was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by my Contrivance. He ever after employed me in his difficult Affairs, and admitted me into his private Council; An Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that a Slave could never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the <hi>Turks</hi> Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>We made ſome ſtay in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Climſan,</hi> in which time I took notice of many Particulars of the ſeveral manners of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are theſe; <hi>Empaſing,</hi> They thruſt a ſharp Stake into the Body of the Criminal, which enters in between their Legs, and appears again at their Mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:104773:95"/> This is their uſual way of treating notable Robbers, and Fellows that have acted againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: It is cruel and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane; for it puts the Patient to a long Pain when the Stake hath eſcap'd the Heart, and ſome of the more ſenſible Parts: Some I have ſeen alive near ſix hours in this manner.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that commit Adultery, or that attempt any thing againſt the Lives of them whom they ſhould defend, are caſt headlong down a Precipice, at the bottom whereof ſharp Stakes are erected to welcome them, and diſpatch them into another World. I have heard ſad Groans and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries from ſuch that have been thus executed.</p>
            <p>There is another manner of Execution, not uſual in our Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates; when any have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <pb n="182" facs="tcp:104773:96"/> Sacriledge, or done any Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the diſhonour of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or the Religion profeſſed in this place, they poure ſcalding Lead into his Mouth, which ſinks in with a horrible Smoke, and burns the Throat to the Entrails: I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard any give the leaſt ſhrick; for the burning Metal conſumes all before it, and cauſes the Wind-pipe to ſhrink.</p>
            <p>Others are expoſed to the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of the Children, who with ſharp Sticks and Canes do prick them to death, that they might accuſtom theſe young Spirits to Blood and Wounds, that when they grow to age they might leſs abhor it. I have ſeen them take a great delight to thruſt their ſharp Reeds into the Sides and Back of the poor Criminal, who is not able to defend himſelf, but with his Tongue; for his Hands
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:104773:96"/> and Legs are tyed in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he may only walk. It is a very pitiful Spectacle to ſee a poor Creature bleed out his Soul through ſo many Wounds. The ſportful Outcries and Voices of the Children do hinder the dying men from being heard. Some of them continue alive many hours, ſprinkling their blood wherever they crawl.</p>
            <p>There is here another as ſtrange an Execution as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; In the great Market place of the City a brazen Lion ſtands, hollow within, with a grim and threatning Countenance, at his Side a Door opens, which is made to receive thoſe that are to be executed in that manner. They are perſons that are guilty of ſome horrid Crimes, and that have offended the Publick in a grievous manner. To recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe <pb n="184" facs="tcp:104773:97"/> them therefore by their Deaths, they execute them thus, that they that have been uſeleſs in their Lives, may give ſome ſport at leaſt at their going out of the world to the People; they are ſhut into this new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a Fire of Wood is kindled under it, which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, as it heats the Braſs, it puts them to a greater torture: The pain forces them to complain and cry out.</p>
            <p>Now at the Mouth, Ears, and under the Tail of the Lion are holes artificially made, out of which the Complaints and Cries of the Patient do burſt forth through different Windings and Turnings, in ſuch a manner that ſeveral Voices, or rather Tunes, are framed one after another; for the Cry is longer a coming out of the Tail than the Ears, and <pb n="185" facs="tcp:104773:97"/> ſo of the Mouth: Beſides, the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Cries yields a pleaſant and a various ſound to the Ears of the Spectators. This cruel ſport continues many times a whole day, to divert the people; for at the Judges pleaſure they kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a leſſer or a greater Fire, which cauſes the Patient to die accordingly. I could never learn the Author of this inhumane En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine which hath been died with ſo much blood; for during my three years abode in that place, I ſaw above twenty caſt into that Oven. A Woman, a Child and a Man were put in together; for it is very large: Their Crime was that they had attempted to kill our Governour, by the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitation of a <hi>Moriſco</hi> Prince that hated him. The Woman was to trapan and enſnare him with her Beauty, and convey ſecretly ſome <pb n="186" facs="tcp:104773:98"/> poiſon by that means into his Drink, when ſhe ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into his Familiarity, and in caſe that Plot did not ſucceed, then the man was to ſtab or ſhoot him when he could meet him at an advantage. Our old General was not ſo aged but he had ſome Reliques of his youthful Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; when therefore he ſaw her Beautiful Eyes, large and full of Spirits, he laboured to get into her more intimate Acquaintance, thinking to meet there with a perfect happineſs; he employed ſuch means as he quickly compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Deſign, but not to his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction ſo much as was expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for as they were together, ſhe diſcovered a Box which ſhe was ſo deſirous to hide from him, that he became ſuſpitious that it might be ſomething that he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not: Aſſoon as he ſaw <pb n="187" facs="tcp:104773:98"/> it, he judged it to be poiſon; but to be more aſſured, he tried it upon a Dog, which ſuffered the ſtrength of it inſtead of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and died within an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taking of it. The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man confeſſed her deſign, and that her Husband was one that intended to perform what ſhe had failed to do, in another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. They were both taken, with an innocent Boy about twelve years of Age, and all three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned together; the Child on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he had ſuch deſperate and wicked Parents, to imprint a greater terror into the minds of ſuch Offenders for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: There was no regard had to Innocency it ſelf: The poor Child was forced to accompany his Parents in Death, as well as in the purſuance of their unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Deſign. Their different Voices
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:104773:99"/> and cries did yield a moſt pleaſant although a cruel Harmony, which was not ungrateful to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who never pity the
<hi>Moors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They uſe in this City ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as well as the
<hi>Turks</hi> in other places, and Drowning with a Stone tied to the neck, executing by Beaſts, by the Sword, and ſuch other ſorts of Death, common in other places.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there is another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of executing Offenders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to this place, which I never heard to be practiſed in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is as cruel as it is ſtrange to us. Out of the Town is planted a high Poſt in form of a Croſs, upon which the Offender is laid; they firſt ſtrip him na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and cut out his Tongue, then they ſtretch him on the Poſt that lies acroſs, and tye him to it both by his hands and feet: thus they
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:104773:99"/> expoſe him to the fury of the ravenous Birds, that ſoon ſmell him out. The Eagles and Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do diſpatch him in leſs than a day: The poor Creature lies at their mercy; he ſees them fix their ſharp Bills in his fleſh, and pluck out his Heart, not being able to reſiſt them; he ſees him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf become a Prey to the Birds of the Air; which cannot but trouble him, to behold ſuch baſe Creatures feed themſelves with his Fleſh, and inſult over him, without the leaſt reſpect to his humanity. It is obſerved, that the Eagles ſeek firſt for the Heart; they tear up the Breſt till they have found it, without any regard to the reſt of the Body, until that be devoured. Sometimes Twenty of theſe great Birds are ſeen at one time upon a poor Man, for this part
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:104773:100"/> of the world is full of them. It is a ſight that may move any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies compaſſion, but that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> to ſee one of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thus torn and ript up by theſe cruel Birds: I was never ſo much concern'd at any thing in my life as I was at it: Had I not feared the Cenſure of the Law, I had ventured to protect the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Body of one poor man from the thoſe ravenous Birds; but it is no leſs than death to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Execution of the Judges Sentence.</p>
            <p>The leſſer Offences are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a milder manner, but in ſuch, as renders the perſons lame, and diſables them from all bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs for a long time after; the <hi>Baſtinado</hi> either upon the Back, the Belly, or the Soles of the Feet, is very common upon any light occaſion. The cutting off <pb n="191" facs="tcp:104773:100"/> of the Ears, Noſe, and other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Ornaments of the Body is uſual.</p>
            <p>Beſides, they brand others in the Forehead with a Character ſignifying the Crime that they have committed.</p>
            <p>They impriſon ſome, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them long at a ſhort allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Bread and Water to tame their ſpirits. In this City, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Governour that commands the Caſtle, there is in the Town a Magiſtrate called an <hi>Alcalde,</hi> an <hi>Arabian</hi> born, ſubject to the <hi>Turks</hi> Power, who amongſt the Citizens does Juſtice to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one: He is aſſiſted by nine cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the nine parts of the Town; all together do ſit upon the publick Buſineſs: The plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Voices alwaies carries it. They judge of all matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Towns-people, as <pb n="190" facs="tcp:104773:101"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:104773:101"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:104773:102"/> the Governour doth of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia.</p>
            <p>The Countrey round about is very fruitful of all ſorts of Corn; for it is Champaign Ground, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with many freſh water Sources and pleaſant Rivulets: Here is abundance of Wheat, Barley, Rice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Oats, they grow Wild in the places that are not Ploughed; every Spring cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Roots to ſhoot out, and produce again this Grain; for the heat of the Summer renders all things unfruitful, as the humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the Winter doth reſtore unto them their native fertility.</p>
            <p>The Commodities of this Place are many; the ordinary, are Oyl, Ginger, Silk, Raiſins, a Stuff made of the Barks of Trees, which the Inhabitants cauſe to be Dyed in all ſorts of Colours; Balm, which is here of ſuch an <pb n="193" facs="tcp:104773:102"/> excellent nature, that it is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Remedy to all Wounds, within the ſpace of four and twenty hours it cloſeth and heals a Cut in the Fleſh. Here is alſo many ſorts of Drugs, which our Merchants fetch from the <hi>Indies,</hi> with vaſt Coſt and Labour. In ſome places here is a golden Sand, which, if any induſtrious People did ſee and enjoy it, I think they might reduce it to true Gold, by refining all the ſandy and droſſy part; but the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants make little uſe of it.</p>
            <p>In the Deſert Places of this Kingdom, are great quantity of Creatures, whoſe skin makes the excellent Buff; they are about the bigneſs of an Ox, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Joints at their Feet, therefore they can hardly riſe when they fall; they run very ſwiftly: The Inhabitants take them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; <pb n="194" facs="tcp:104773:103"/> They obſerve the place where theſe Beaſts do rub them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; if it be a Tree, they cut the Stump, and prop it up in ſuch a manner that it ſtands up, ready to fall at the leaſt violence; when theſe Beaſts come to their uſual place, they rub according to their cuſtome, leaning themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the broken Tree, which falls, and they after it. Here are other ſorts of beaſts ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in our Climates: Tigers are here of an extraordinary bigneſs, with Leopards, wild Aſſes, wild Horſes with a tumor in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head that is hard; which may have occaſioned the Fable of the Unicorn; for in ſome it ſhoots out in ſuch a manner that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears like unto a Horn of a white Colour, of a Cubit long. The Horſes are all either white or black: The <hi>Moors</hi> name them
<hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicoughs.</hi> 
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:104773:103"/> I never ſaw any tam'd. They are ſo ſwift in running that no Horſe can follow them; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are ſurprized when they come near the inhabited Countrey, and are kill'd with Guns, but it is a difficult buſineſs to catch them alive; their young ones are very wild and ſwift, and are of a ruddy colour until they come to be a year old.</p>
            <p>There is here a great number of Oſtriches; it is a notable bird, that runs and flies very ſpeedily; no Creature is able to keep pace with it. Many extraordinary things are reported of it. The Countrey people ſay that they do ſometimes find their Neſts in the Sands: They make them in this manner; they ſcrape a round Pit as large as their body, where they place their Eggs in order. They lay above a hundred before <pb n="196" facs="tcp:104773:104"/> they cauſe them to bring forth, not in a heap, but in ſeveral ranks; the Sun-beams warm them and cauſe them to burſt forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to birds; the Mother-Oſtrich o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlooks them, and when the firſt laid Eggs are become birds, ſhe takes the farthermoſt Eggs to feed them until they come of age and ſtrength to walk alone. It is a Creature that is careleſs of her Fruit until they are birds, and then ſhe nouriſhes them with care, giving equally to all, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby her Juſtice. She is a bird very temperate, content with a ſmall quantity of food, and able to digeſt the hardeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as Iron, Steel, and Stones.</p>
            <p>Near the City is a Fountain of a ſtrange nature; it yields a plentiful Stream, when the Moon is in its Full, then the Water is
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:104773:104"/> boiling hot; but it cools by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees as the Moon decreaſes, and becomes extream cold when it is the laſt day; the Stream alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming leſſer or greater accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. When any are troubled with the Gout or any other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe in the Limbs, they repair thither from all parts to be waſht in that Water, that is brackiſh. I have known many that have been cured in the Bath that is joining to it, by waſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeveral days in the full Moon.</p>
            <p>One thing more renders this Place famous all over the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and cauſeth people from all parts to reſort to it: Here is the Tomb of a great <hi>Hage,</hi> not much inferiour to <hi>Mahomet</hi> in the eſteem of this People, as much reſpected by all that fancy to have received any benefit from <pb n="198" facs="tcp:104773:105"/> their Pilgrimages hither. Men or Women that are troubled with Iſſues of blood, Agues, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, Dropſies, and many other Diſeaſes, do take a great deal of pains to come and pay their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to the Coffin of this old Saint, renowned in his Life time for Phyſick, and after his Death, the <hi>Moors</hi> have fancied that his bones and Reliques had ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary virtue contained in them, which they ſeek to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of by their Devotions in this place. So eaſie a thing it is to perſwade the Ignorant Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to Superſtition: When men are eſteemed for ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary qualities, the People fancy that theſe qualities do yet accompany them in their graves, that they are inſeparable from their bodies. The Heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols were increaſed by this means <pb n="199" facs="tcp:104773:105"/> to that vaſt Army of Gods, and <hi>Rome</hi> hath fill'd her Oratories with an innumerable company of petty Saints by this Expedient; for it is ordinary in the Popiſh Dominions to make them paſs for Saints that have excelled in any particular Art or Knowledge, when that Generation is dead that hath been acquainted with the Vices and Weakneſſes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there is at a League diſtant from the City, towards the Eaſt, the Ruines of an old Tower, and about it a large Cave, where, as the People of the Town report, are frequent Appearances of Devils and evil Spirits that diſturb the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at certain Seaſons of the Year; ſome told me that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts was kept the Witches Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, a general Meeting of <pb n="200" facs="tcp:104773:106"/> thoſe deſperate Souls that own the Devils Power. It is believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the people that this place is dangerous in the night, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I never ſaw any thing worſe than my ſelf when I have paſt that way, going about my Maſters buſineſs in all times of the day and night. But when ſuch kind of Reports are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed into the Fancy of the People, the leaſt teſtimony of a timorous perſon that hears the ſhaking of a Leaf is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them in that belief, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can remove it out of their minds. I do not doubt but ſome Appearances have been of Evil Spirits; none but a Phantaſtick Sadducee is able to deny this Truth that hath all Ages to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it; but we muſt not be of ſo light a belief as to credit all the idle Reports of Appearances <pb n="201" facs="tcp:104773:106"/> of Devils which fly amongſt the vulgar ſort of people.</p>
            <p>In this City of <hi>Tremiſen</hi> or <hi>Clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan</hi> we made our abode longer than my Maſter at firſt deſigned; but his good Services to them of <hi>Argiers</hi> deſerved no leſs than a grateful acknowledgement, by advancing him to a higher, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, ſuch as might reward him.</p>
            <p>At the return of the year, when the <hi>Turks</hi> Army came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve us, my Maſter had order to be Lieutenant Governour of the City, and to remain ſtill as long as he ſhould judge it convenient for his Intereſt. This place proved very beneficial to him, becauſe he had the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Parties that did march out in the Fields to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the Enemy; and when the Governour was pleaſed to go <pb n="202" facs="tcp:104773:107"/> out himſelf towards the Borders, my Maſter had the Governours ſmall Fees, that did amount to a conſiderable ſum in ſuch a large City. During this time that we dwelt in this place ſeveral nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Affairs happened, which may claim a part in this Relation: The unconſtant <hi>Arabians</hi> did often riſe and trouble our peace, by their frequent Incurſions; the King of
<hi>Fez,</hi> made an Inroad as far as our City with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Body of Horſe, thinking to ſurprize it unawares. Several other Princes were troubleſome to us, obliging our people to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual Tributes and Cuſtomes when they paſſed through their Countrey; for this City enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a great Trade with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land people, and with the <hi>Blacks.</hi> It was therefore the <hi>Turks</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to entertain it, and remove
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:104773:107"/> all Obſtructions wich might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a free Intercourſe: For that intent we had ſeveral troubleſom Buſineſſes both Warlike and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, which employed my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all the time of his being there. In the mean whiles I was not idle; I had ſeveral Affairs that concerned my private Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and that I was to manage with Care and Induſtry. The <hi>Sultan</hi> of <hi>Argeirs</hi> gave a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Ability and Perſon, which was not contradicted by the Women with whom I was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards acquainted.</p>
            <p>I had as difficult Encounters, and as ſtrange Adventures that happened to me with them, as my Maſter had in treating with the
<hi>Arabs.</hi> I was no ſooner ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>Climſan,</hi> but one of that Sex ſought a fair occaſion to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her Affection to me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:104773:108"/>I was very wary how I entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any ſuch Propoſition; for I was affraid of my Maſters Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or any other Plot which might be ſet on foot to drive me to a neceſſity of turning
<hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan;</hi> for I was often impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd by my Maſter, and invited with the promiſe of my Liberty, in caſe I would renounce Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; but I could never conſent to ſo much weakneſs, nor to act againſt ſo much Light God had diſcovered to me in his Truth. I was therefore affraid that all addreſſes that were made to me of that nature were but Deſignes to enſnare me, and oblige me to Apoſtacie. I did not accept of ſo fair opportunities as were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to me, which created me a great deal of trouble; for thoſe perſons became my deadly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they ſought all occaſions
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:104773:108"/> to do me miſchief: Angered Love turns into deadly hatred. The firſt whoſe Careſſes I was to ſuffer was the Wife of a wealthy Citizen of <hi>Climſan;</hi> her Husband was old and decrepit, and ſhe very young, and therefore more pardonable if ſhe ſought ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction abroad, when ſhe could not find it at home. I was often ſent to her Houſe for things that my Maſter wanted; there ſhe began to be acquainted with me.</p>
            <p>The Women in this Countrey keep much at home, but their Minds and Affections are more wandring abroad, becauſe they are ſo recluſe; whereas if they had as much liberty as in other Countries, they would not be ſo furiouſly debauch'd: Their Husbands alſo keep ſuch ſtrict guard over them, that when they can eſcape their Eyes, they <pb n="206" facs="tcp:104773:109"/> give the reins to their Paſſion, and labour to ſatisfie themſelves more abundantly; ſtoln waters are ſweet: The more they are forbidden and hindered from variety, the more pleaſure and ſatisfaction they fancy in it.</p>
            <p>It is not to be imagined what tricks and invention this Woman had to draw me into her Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: She began to declare her kindneſs by offering unto me ſome preſents when I came to her Dwelling: I never went but ſhe gave me ſomething to carry back for my ſelf, diſcourſing with me very freely when her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was not in the way. I did not know unto what period this growing paſſion might riſe, nor what ſad conſequences might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; therefore I did ſhun her company as much as I could: Still ſhe laboured to win me with her <pb n="207" facs="tcp:104773:109"/> Kindneſs. At one time her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being not at home, aſſoon as I was entred ſhe diſcovered her face unto me, and took me by the hand to lead me into a private Room; I followed her, not thinking at that preſent of her meaning; we were no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er entred, but without fear or ſhame ſhe began to wooe me with all the Expreſſions of tenderneſs imaginable. I was in a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and haſte, and not willing to ſubmit: My reſiſtance did yet more enflame her; whiles we were thus diſputing, ſhe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me, and I to diſſwade her, in ſteps her Husband in the other Room next to us; his ſudden ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival ſcared us both; for we had not eſcaped his jealous Fury, had he ſeen me in ſo private a place with his Wife; but there was no time to deliberate, nor way <pb n="208" facs="tcp:104773:110"/> to eſcape but through the Door; the danger therefore made her ingenious, and find out this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient; ſhe roſe from me, and with a chearful Countenance meets her Husband at the Door, taking him by the hand, <hi>Ziddi, Ziddi,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I am glad you are come home, in the Back-ſide of our houſe is the ſtrangest thing that ever you ſaw,</hi> and with that led him to ſee a Beaſt that my Maſter had ſent him, whilſt I eſcaped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, glad to have ſaved my life. This danger could not make the Woman wiſe; ſhe yet continued her Love unto me, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing me many times into the greateſt Inconveniences, becauſe of her doting Husband, that did ſurprize us talking together in a too familiar manner. She did ſtill importune me with her Kindneſs, and by that means the old Fool <pb n="209" facs="tcp:104773:110"/> began to be ſo affraid of me that he was ready to ſtab me. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the buſineſs to my Maſter, and made him the Confident of that Love. He began to admire my Continency and good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and deſired me, if I were ſo reſerved, that I would pleaſure him by giving him a favourable Meeting with that Lady; for it ſeems he was grown amorous of her; but her fair Face, which made her be eſteemed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Beauty of the City, made her Husband to watch over her day and night, for fear ſhe ſhould taſt of forbidden Fruit. My Maſter was glad at this diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he grumbled at me that I had not ſooner declared it unto him, aſſuring me that I might have been more confident with him: I excuſed my ſelf, and told him that had I known his pleaſure, he
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:104773:111"/> ſhould have been already ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I promiſed to ſerve him faithfully in this buſineſs, in caſe he would appeaſe the fury of her jealous Husband, who did threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me with death if I came near his houſe; he engaged to do it, which accordingly he performed; ſo that I was admitted again into the Citizens dwelling, and had there the ſame freedom as before. The Womans paſſion was not ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with her Husbands Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Jealouſie; ſhe ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued her kindneſs to me: I began for my Maſters ſake to be more tractable; I promiſed her full ſatisfaction, but told her that I did not dare to venture into her Houſe; ſhe offered me any other Rendezvous; I mentioned my Maſters Houſe unto her; ſhe promiſed to find ſome Expedient to eſcape thither within a day or <pb n="211" facs="tcp:104773:111"/> two; I took my leave of her, ſealing my Affection in the woot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed manner, which ſhe accepted of with thoſe tranſports of joy that become a paſſionate Lover. I left her full of hopes and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, meditating upon ſome Expedient how to procure unto her ſelf a ſafe eſcape, free from the ſuſpition of her jealous Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; a thing very difficult to find, becauſe Jealouſie hath a hundred Eyes, and many times where they ſhould not be; the leaſt ſtep abroad would but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the trouble of the doating Fool, eſpecially if ſhe was ſeen to come in ſight of the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>In the Houſe, beſides himſelf, was an old Woman, and other people apt to tell Tales of one Renowned for that they would willingly have. Envy in ſuch caſes is apt to ſpeak and invent <pb n="212" facs="tcp:104773:112"/> more than is agreeable to Truth. The Ladies Love was not fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all theſe difficulties; it found out a way to ſatisfie its ſelf: As her Husband was at Supper with her, ſhe infuſed into his Drink the Juice of an Herb that provoketh to ſleep. After the repaſt they went to their reſt, ſending their Servants alſo to theirs, ſhe had been careful to take into her cuſtody the Keys of the Door. The poor man was no ſooner upon his Quilt with this amorous Woman, but he fell into a dead ſleep; in the mean whiles, ſhe riſes, and comes with all ſpeed up to the Caſtle: My Maſter having been acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all that had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, had given order to the Sentinel, not to examine too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly one in a womans habit that ſhould come at ſuch an hour. <pb n="213" facs="tcp:104773:112"/> She found the Guard very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to her, and my Maſters Lodging far more; for he was prepared to receive her with as much civillity as ſhe did deſire: She quickly returned muffled up, and laid her ſelf down by her drowſie Husband, as if nothing had paſſed to his prejudice.</p>
            <p>When Women once loſe their honeſty, nothing can keep them from that pleaſure which they fancy ſo ſweet. This Woman having found ſo good entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the firſt, was reſolved to make a ſecond tryal of our Kindneſs. She continued to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit us, as often as her induſtry could find an eſcape, until the Old Mans furious Jealouſie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled her from walking abroad.</p>
            <p>Had my deſign been to make Conqueſts in the Empire of Love, I think none could have <pb n="214" facs="tcp:104773:113"/> been more happy. When a Man is got into the eſteem of Women, his Fame reſts not in one or two Breaſts, but ſpeaks as loud, and with as many tongues as theſe prating Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The old Citizens Wife had whiſpered ſome of her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets to her intimate Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and they to others, ſo that this good opinion of my Ability ſpread &amp; increaſed wonderfully in the Town; it created me ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations, and no little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to avoid them. Had I been unconſtant in Religion, I had made great advantage in this place of the Womens Kindneſs to me; but here I could not fix without Apoſtacy, which was too big a Morſel for my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſwallow. That which was the moſt powerful temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was offered to me by a rich <pb n="215" facs="tcp:104773:113"/> Heireſs, widow to a former Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, of the moſt conſiderable amongſt the Citizens; ſhe ſent to know from my Maſter whether he would part with me for any Money; he anſwered, that he could not ſell me becauſe I had deſerved my Freedom, and that he had promiſed it unto me. When Gold (which finds in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places but a faint reſiſtance) would not do, another Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent was ſet on foot; a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or an <hi>Arabian Zidi</hi> addreſt himſelf to my Maſter and me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, telling us his buſineſs in ſhort, That there was a rich Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, no leſs handſom, without Charge of Children, that was deſirous to make me her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and to give me all her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate if I would become <hi>Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and remain in that place. My Maſter hearkened to this <pb n="216" facs="tcp:104773:114"/> Propoſition for the Love he had for me, &amp; began to exaggerate my good Fortune, and the happineſs that was offered to me, wiſhing me to accept of it, and not to ſuffer ſo great a loſs for the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Religion. My firſt Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution was to deſpiſe all theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and to prefer the Life of a Slave with Honour, and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion before the greateſt Riches and the moſt pleaſant Life: I remained ſtill in it. All my Maſters perſwaſions could not ſhake me from it, when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered within my ſelf ſuch an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to deny my Saviour that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me, to deſpiſe his Bloud, to renounce all intereſt in him, to abjure his Truth, that I knew to be ſuch, and own an Impoſtor <hi>(Mahomet);</hi> to prefer him and his Diabolical Religion before that which Chriſt hath eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:104773:114"/> this action appeared unto me with ſuch an horrid Aſpect that I was frighted from the very thoughts of it: All the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages propoſed to me, the vaſt Riches &amp; Revenues could make no Impreſſion upon my ſpirit; I foreſaw alſo that if I ever did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my ſelf in that Countrey by eſpouſing ſo great an intereſt in it, I ſhould with more difficulty bring to paſs my eſcape, and that inſtead of purchaſing my Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at ſuch a dear rate, I ſhould but enſlave my ſelf more, and in ſuch a manner, that there would be ſmall hopes left of ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain my Native Soil. Theſe Conſiderations preſerved my mind from this powerful temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that wanted not Art, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and Power to ſecond it; but when my Maſter ſaw my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and how unpleaſing the
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:104773:115"/> change of Religion was to me, he deſired them never to mention unto me ſuch a matter again. He would never after ſuffer any ſuch Propoſition to be made to me, wiſhing that I might live and die in it. By that I perceived that he was inclined to favour Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, and that Renegades are never grateful to the <hi>Turks,</hi> although they embrace their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; Unconſtancy and Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are odious to them alſo that receive a benefit by the Traitors. My refuſal did diſappoint the
<hi>Mooriſh</hi> Lady, but did not put a ſtop to her proceedings; ſhe imagined all the ways poſſible to enjoy what ſhe ſo paſſionately deſired. She contrived the means to ſpeak to me her ſelf privately; ſhe laboured to trepan me, and drive me to a neceſſity of burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or turning, hoping to obtain <pb n="219" facs="tcp:104773:115"/> more eaſily her end; but all was in vain: I had conſtancy enough, and was ſufficiently wary, to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate all her undertakings.</p>
            <p>When ſhe ſaw her ſelf diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of all her hopes, which ſhe had conceived from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer means employed to woe me, ſhe gave not over; her Paſſion was more enflamed with this ſtout reſiſtance, ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſolved to find out ſome other way, to know the truth of what was reported of me: A Curioſity that coſt us both much trouble and hazzard of Life.</p>
            <p>The correſpondency that ſhe aimed at was dangerous, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomething to excuſe and hide it from the Eyes of the World; the beſt Cloak was Marriage, which ſeeing ſhe could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with me, was reſolved to take ſome other that might be <pb n="220" facs="tcp:104773:116"/> favourable to her Paſſion, and give it the liberty of ſatisfying it ſelf; for that intent ſhe addreſſes her ſelf to a poor man of that place, deſcended from good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage of the <hi>Moors,</hi> but his Fortunes were not anſwerable to his Nobility; ſeveral Misfortunes had reduced him to almoſt a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging condition, and he had lately loſt by death his Wife, which during her life he was ſcarce able to maintain. The <hi>Moriſco</hi> Lady acquaints him by a truſty Friend with her good inclinations for him, and appoints unto him both the place and time to ſpeak with him further about this buſineſs; he joyfully accepts of the Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, hoping by this means to redeem himſelf and Children from extream poverty and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: At the time he comes to the place, and there meets with <pb n="221" facs="tcp:104773:116"/> the Lady, who having diſmiſſed all other Company &amp; Witneſſes, freely diſcovers unto him her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for me, and my ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Repulſe, and her Reſolution to beſtow her ſelf and Means up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a Husband that would not ſearch too narrowly into her Actions, but that would give her the liberty of receiving the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits of thoſe perſons that ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved paſſionately. The poor man ſaw that what was propoſed to him was offenſive to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but advantageous to his Purſe. In the condition he was in he could not reaſonably refuſe the Offer, although it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to his Credit; he was therefore willing to become a Cuckold to enjoy the Riches of this Widow, hoping after Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to behave himſelf with her in ſuch a manner, that he would <pb n="222" facs="tcp:104773:117"/> reclaim her from thoſe idle and unlawful fancies: The Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was agreed to, and all things concluded on; the Marriage was performed with as much ſecrecy and with as little Ceremony as was poſſible. When it came to the knowledge of her Friends, they laboured to divert her from it, but ſhe was ſo obſtinately reſolved, that nothing could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her from her deſign; which was no ſooner accompliſhed, but ſhe laboured to find the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſhe ſought after: Her Husband kept not his word with her; he fell into a fit of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that would neither ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her to ſee the Air, nor me to come near her Dwelling; ſo that ſhe was forced to uſe her wit, to get what ſhe had bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained for. When the Fool grew rich, he forgot his Benefactor,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:104773:117"/> and remembred no more his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to her, never to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb and perſecute her for Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gallantry and Pleaſure. He ſeldom met me in the ſtreets, but he ſought all occaſions to ſtab and ſhoot me, daring not to vent his anger upon her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of her powerful Friends, that were not pleaſed with the unequal Match.</p>
            <p>Whiles I remained in this place, I have run ſeveral other misfortunes; many other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did deſire to be acquainted with me: I was once ſo troubled with addreſſes, that I wiſhed my Face had been disfigured, my ſtature more contemptible, and that all the promiſing Characters of my perſon had never appeared in me: At laſt, I made my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron privy to all my Affairs; his favour did wonderfully protect
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:104773:118"/> me: None did dare to make any attempt upon my perſon, when he had publiſhed the kindneſs he had for me; otherwiſe I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returned from this City, but had left my Bones amongſt theſe Heathens. It is true, I did him ſometimes the favour to cauſe him to ſhare with me in my good Fortune, and furthered the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of his Inclinations, an Office not ungrateful to an old Lover, that hath ſcarce any thing acceptable in him, but the deſire of well doing.</p>
            <p>During this time that we did ſpend in <hi>Climſan,</hi> an accident happened that cauſed us to make another Journey into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey with about 1500 men. The King of <hi>Fez, Bembouker</hi> by name, had ſent out a Party to ſtop a Caravan of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Blacks,</hi> that brought a conſiderable <pb n="225" facs="tcp:104773:118"/> quantity of Gold from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Countrey to our City: There were near about thirty Cammels loaden with Gold, and other Commodities of <hi>Guiny:</hi> It ſeems the Merchants were jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the intentions of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs</hi> about <hi>Fez,</hi> and therefore had divided their Caravan, and ſent ſix Cammels one way, with the moſt contemptible part of the Goods, carrying the reſt by another, that whiles they did ſeize upon the leſſer part, the greater might eſcape out of their Territories.</p>
            <p>We had notice that a Party was upon the Road to wait for this Booty: Our Governour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſpatch'd my Maſter with 1500 men, well armed, to watch them. We could not make ſuch ſpeed, but they had before our arrival taken the ſix Cammels <pb n="226" facs="tcp:104773:119"/> loaden, and were driving them another way to <hi>Fez;</hi> aſſoon as we heard of this News, we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them, and about ten Leagues on this ſide of <hi>Fez,</hi> in the aſcent of a Mountain we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertook them; my Maſter was obliged in honour not to let them eſcape out of his hands, but to fight them, although they were far more in number than the <hi>Turks;</hi> he therefore thought it his ſafeſt courſe to advance before them by a ſecret way, and lay an Ambuſcado at the Deſcent of the Mountain, where a large Wood did ſtretch it ſelf along the ſides of the next Plain; we therefore took a ſmall compaſs about undiſcovered; for they marched very ſecure, not dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we had intelligence of all their Deſignes. We arrived to the place before them; my <pb n="227" facs="tcp:104773:119"/> Maſter diſpoſed of his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in ſeveral convenient places in the Woods, and as the <hi>Arabs</hi> came up to the middle of us, we then gave them a Salute with our Shot from both ſides of the way, whiles a party of our men that was behind, did riſe up from the place by which the <hi>Arabs</hi> had paſſed, and came riding in all ſpeed to them. The Fight was deſperate and bloody; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were ſurprized, they held out a longer while than we could imagin, charging us again and again, until there came up two freſh Companies of choice Foot, that met them in the way that they were to paſs. They were no ſooner perceived by the <hi>Arabs,</hi> but they began to faint, and think of a Retreat; for they were afraid to be incloſed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they all joined in a cloſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <pb n="228" facs="tcp:104773:120"/> reſolving to break through thoſe ſmall Numbers that lay in their way; our men divided themſelves on both ſides, and as they paſſed, they arreſted about a hundred of theſe luſty Robbers, that fell to the ground half dead with the ſhot that had wounded them. About 60 of our men loſt their Lives, and about 300 <hi>Arabians</hi> left us their Horſes and Cloathing for Legacies, with our own Goods that they had taken. Our Horſe purſued the Enemy, but not very far for fear of a like Ambuſcado; the Countrey being proper for ſuch Tricks and Sratagems of War. They brought back with them wounded ſome Priſoners, and a few Horſes. We enquired from the <hi>Blacks</hi> &amp; two of our Merchants what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the reſt of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; for we had heard how they <pb n="229" facs="tcp:104773:120"/> had ſeparated the <hi>Caravan;</hi> they informed us of the By-way they had taken, reſolved to die rather than to quit their Goods: They were in number about 300 men that came with the Camels. My Maſter ſent all that he had recovered to <hi>Climſan</hi> with a ſmall Guard, conducting them part of the way as far as <hi>Gorſelveh,</hi> a ſmall Town about ten miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Climſan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We then marched back again with all the reſt of our men, to meet the other part of our <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravan</hi> that was come to the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Province of <hi>Segelmes,</hi> by a ſecret way unknown to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons. They could never come ſo ſecretly but the <hi>Arabs,</hi> (ſome were of thoſe we had beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) did lie in wait for them, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to meet with better Fortune <pb n="230" facs="tcp:104773:121"/> than in the former Encounters, and to recompenſe themſelves for their late Loſſes.</p>
            <p>Our men did defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deſperately; but had we not opportunely appeared to their Aſſiſtance, they had been overpowered with the Numbers of <hi>Arabs</hi> &amp; <hi>Moors.</hi> We no ſooner appeared among them, which was in a Valley, watered with ſome Branches of the River called now by the Inhabitants <hi>Soubhir.</hi> Our People were on the other ſide of the River, and the <hi>Moors</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs</hi> on this, between both was a little Ford eaſie to paſs. The Diſpute had been long when we arrived; for the Enemy did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to paſs, and our men did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them.</p>
            <p>Our coming ended the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; for they no ſooner ſaw us appear, but they fled away in <pb n="231" facs="tcp:104773:121"/> all haſte. We contented our ſelves to have preſerved our Goods, we did not therefore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, but marched towards <hi>Climſan,</hi> where our Arrival was joyfully expected; for here all the chief perſons of the Town were intereſſed. This <hi>Caravan</hi> did enrich us, and fill the City with plenty of Gold, Ivory and other Commodities, which were conveyed to <hi>Argeirs</hi> and other places on the Sea-Coaſt, to be tranſported by Sea to
<hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Maſter and the Chief of the Party that went out, were well rewarded for their pains; the reſt did ſhare amongſt them the Horſes that were taken from the <hi>Arabs,</hi> and their Cloaths, which were prized at a great ſum of Money. My Maſter had the honour of the good ſucceſs; for <pb n="232" facs="tcp:104773:122"/> every one did attribute it to his wiſe Conduct and Valour. My Company was not unuſeful to him; for beſides the Service I did render him in the firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, I ſaved him when he was in no little danger of his life; had I not been near to aſſiſt him, doubtleſs he had been ſent to convey the dead into the other world. He acknowledged my Care and Love for him by his continual Kindneſs for me; for he did not treat me as a Slave, but as a Friend, granting me as much Liberty as I could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>After this Expedition we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained about a year in
<hi>Climſan,</hi> during which time ſeveral Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents hapned; the great
<hi>Moſque</hi> of the City fell to the ground by a terrible Earthquake, and frighted the reſt of the City; a <pb n="233" facs="tcp:104773:122"/> few Houſes joining to this Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious place with their Inhabitants were buried in the Ruines.</p>
            <p>Two Stars of a good bigneſs flew over the City; they were followed by ſeveral other little Lights; they met all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one point, and made a great Star, that hung over the City about three days: The Aſtrologers and Negromancers of the Countrey were conſulted about the meaning of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors; they all agreed that they were ſignificant and Prophetical. All the little Lights that joined to make a great one, they ſaid were ſeveral little Principalities that would unite together to compoſe a great Monarchy that would not favour the <hi>Turks</hi> in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>The Inhabitants are very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious when any ſuch Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <pb n="234" facs="tcp:104773:123"/> do appear in the Firmament; they run to their
<hi>Moſquets,</hi> and fall to their Devotions, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all other buſineſs many days; for they never interpret ſuch Signes to their advantage, they look upon them as dreadful fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of publick Calamities. The people of this place were ſo much the more concerned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe Signes did appear on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that Region, and did hang over their City in a threatning manner.</p>
            <p>Another thing very extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hapned about the ſame time: A ſtrange Monſter was born of a <hi>Moriſco</hi> Woman; it had the Head of an Ape, the Feet of a Gooſe, the Body of a Man, the Hands like the Claws of a Lion; many perſons went to ſee it; Several Reports were ſpread about the Town concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="235" facs="tcp:104773:123"/> theſe unuſual Accidents, which terrified the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuſceptible of fear upon the leaſt occaſion. Many Dreams alſo were divulged at the ſame time by the
<hi>Turks</hi> Enemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame buſineſs, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deſtruction of the <hi>Turks</hi> Empire in thoſe parts. So that there was likely to be a great Commotion, had not our Governour kept good Orders, and clapt one of theſe buſie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in a deep Dungeon, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his Releaſe from that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that was to deſtroy and drive away the
<hi>Turks;</hi> but the ſilly Raſcal would never expect that Hour; he grew impatient in his Chains, ſo that he employed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of his Friends to mediate for him, and procure from our Governour his Liberty, which was granted upon condition that <pb n="236" facs="tcp:104773:124"/> he would be more diſcreet for the future, and keep his Dreams within the Circumference of his Couch.</p>
            <p>Our Governour could not ſo well order his buſineſs, but that the <hi>Arabs</hi> (forward enough to catch at all Occaſions of ruining the
<hi>Turks</hi>) made ſeveral Parties in the Territories of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, aſſuring the Inhabitants that now was the time that they ſhould pay no more Taxes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the Pride and Luxury of <hi>Argiers,</hi> and that if they would lend their helping hand, it was poſſible to recover from thence what they had ſent from year to year.</p>
            <p>Some, as it alwaies happens on ſuch occaſions, were ſo ſilly to believe them; they formed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeveral little Parties up and down; they were inconſiderable <pb n="237" facs="tcp:104773:124"/> ſeparated, but had they been to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they might have created us much trouble and buſineſs. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies of our Souldiers were ſent out to diſperſe them. The greateſt Body was compoſed of two thouſand Horſe and Foot met together about ſix Leagues from <hi>Climſan,</hi> at a Town called <hi>Tezrim,</hi> which is ſtony by ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Art. Theſe had killed ſome that favoured the <hi>Turks,</hi> and were reſolved to wait there to ſee whether any more would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily join with them.</p>
            <p>My Maſter was ſent out with about 1200 men only, but cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the Garriſon: We laid ſiege to this ſtrong place, and at the end of ſix days it was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to us by Compoſition. The Conditions impoſed were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable; the Inhabitants were condemned to deliver up their
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:104773:125"/> chief Leaders, and part with a Sum of Money. The Leaders were ſacrificed to the <hi>Turks</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and ſent into the other world to raiſe Tumults there.</p>
            <p>One thing I cannot omit very memorable in this place. At ſome diſtance from <hi>Tezrim,</hi> in a little Meadow where excellent Graſs grows, I ſaw the perfect Stature of a man Buggering his Aſs; it was ſo lively that at a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I fancied they had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, but when I came nearer, I ſaw they were of a perfect Stone. I enquired wherefore the
<hi>Moors</hi> or <hi>Arabs,</hi> that naturally hate all ſorts of Repreſentations, ſhould ſhew their Skill by making ſuch Beaſtly Figures, odious to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I was informed that this was never made by man, but that ſome body of former years had been turned into this Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:104773:125"/> with the Aſs in the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Beaſtly Act. God by his power had changed the fleſhly Subſtances of the Man and of the Aſs into a firm Stone, as an eternal reproach to Mankind, and a Juſtification of his ſevere Judgments againſt us.</p>
            <p>I did further ſearch into the Appearances of this Report, and found the Stone to repreſent not only the perfect ſhape, but alſo the colour of every part of the Man and of the Beaſt, with the Sinews, Veins, Eyes, Mouth, in ſuch a lively manner that no Artiſt with all his Colours could expreſs it better; ſo that I was convinced of the Truth of this Report. I did labour to move it, but ſome that were in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did forbid me, telling me that ſome have laboured to tranſport it from thence, but could never <pb n="240" facs="tcp:104773:126"/> away that Monument of mans ſhameful Luſt: Some have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to their peril; either their Perſons or their Cattel, that did attempt it, were ſtruck dead in the place. Gods Juſtice will not ſuffer that to be hid or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that he hath placed there for all to example by it. It is neceſſary that the <hi>Moors</hi> ſhould have ſuch ſignal Tokens of Gods Diſpleaſure always before their Eyes; for they are enraged to commit ſuch filthy Actions more frequently than other Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">An Account of this was Printed 14 years ſince under the name of Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby.</hi>
               </note> I was informed by ſome of my Acquaintance that have been at <hi>Tripoly,</hi> that there is ſome ſuch Monument of Gods Juſtice near that Town about five days Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from it, towards the South-Eaſt <pb n="241" facs="tcp:104773:126"/> amongſt the Mountains cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gubel,</hi> far more notable than this. Many of our
<hi>Engliſh</hi> proteſt they have ſeen ſome pieces of it brought by the <hi>Moors</hi> to <hi>Tripoly,</hi> and heard it confidently reported in Town as an undeniable Truth. Some of our Merchants have had the Curioſity to have gone to that place, and they alſo proteſt it to be true, that in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains about five days Journey from <hi>Tripoly</hi> there is a whole Town full of theſe Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſtones repreſenting all manner of Creatures belonging to a City, with the Houſes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, Beaſts, Trees, Walls, and Rooms, very diſtinctly ſhap'd. Our people have entered into the Houſes, and there they have found a Child in a Cradle, of ſtone; a Woman in a Bed, of ſtone; a man at the Door look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="242" facs="tcp:104773:127"/> Lice, of ſtone; Camels in ſeveral poſtures, of ſtone; a man beating a Woman, of ſtone; two men fighting, of ſtone; Cats, Dogs, Mice, and all that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the place of ſuch perfect ſtone, and ſo well expreſſing the ſeveral Shapes, Poſtures and Paſſions in which the Inhabitants were in that time, that no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graver could do the like. Some may look upon this Relation as Fabulous, but let them enquire of our Merchants, and Traders that have been in that City of <hi>Tripoly,</hi> or in the Land, they ſhall find them all agree in the Confirmation of this Relation. The Report that runs amongſt the <hi>Moors</hi> is, that this Town was very populous and fruitful, as may appear by the Trees of ſtone of ſeveral ſorts of Fruits planted round about it, and in the places <pb n="243" facs="tcp:104773:127"/> that retain the Forms of Gardens and Orchards, when the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants gave themſelves over to all manner of Vices, to the great ſcandal of humane Nature, God in a moment ſtopp'd all their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and turn'd their Bodies into firm Stone, that future Ages might ſee and learn to dread his power.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Athens</hi> there is another ſuch like Figure; a ſtone repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting two men buggering one another. I know no reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould doubt of the poſſibility of theſe Relations, if we conſider the Almighty power of God that cauſeth all things to ſubſiſt by his Influence, and can eaſily alter or change them as it ſeems good to his Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Or if we conſider the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that there ſhould be ſuch notable Examples of Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <pb n="244" facs="tcp:104773:128"/> perpetuated to poſterity, which cannot be but by ſome ſuch manner that it may expreſs his diſpleaſure in future Ages, eſpecially in this Countrey, where the People are addicted to ſuch like Villanies that Nature it ſelf abhors. From thoſe that travel into theſe places every one may better ſatisfie themſelves concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth of theſe wonderful Examples of Gods Juſtice, much like that of <hi>Lot's</hi> Wife turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Pillar of Salt, which ſome very ancient Hiſtorians do affirm to have ſeen remaining in their days.</p>
            <p>We returned after that we had retaken all the Countrey that was revolted, with more honour than profit; for we did make war againſt a needy, poor, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable people, that had ſcarce ſufficient to ſubſiſt; beſides they <pb n="245" facs="tcp:104773:128"/> do craftily hide all their beſt Moveables in difficult and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known places when they engage themſelves in any Revolt, that they may never lament the loſs of the chief part of their ſubſtance. Sometimes hazzard brings their Enemies amongſt their Treaſury, but they are ſo ſecret that no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence can cauſe them to confeſs the place where it is laid up; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Cattel and other Beaſts do become a Prey after the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. In time of peace they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to redeem them by ſtealth and Robbery; for there are no greater Thieves than the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people of this Kingdom: If any ſhould paſs ſingle through their Territories, he is ſure to loſe his Life and all that he hath, by the Peaſants that profeſs the greateſt ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Turks</hi> power.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="246" facs="tcp:104773:129"/>At the coming of the Army from
<hi>Argiers</hi> we took our Bag and Baggage, and returned to that Maritine City. My Maſter was grown very rich and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he had got (beſides a great eſteem which the good Services that he had rendered deſerved) much Wealth. According to his Promiſe he gave me my Liberty, and and a ſum of Money to carry me home. I met then with a <hi>French</hi> Veſſel of
<hi>Marſeilles</hi> in the Harbour; in it I embarked, and ſailed into
<hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="navigation" type="observation">
            <pb n="247" facs="tcp:104773:129"/>
            <head>An Obſervation of the Tide, and how to turn out of the
<hi>Streights-Mouth</hi> the Wind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Westerly: Communicated by the Induſtrious and Experienced Seaman, <hi>Richard Norris.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AT <hi>Tangier,</hi> and <hi>Tariffe,</hi> a South-weſt and by South Moon make a full Sea on the ſhore; but in all parts of the
<hi>Streights-mouth</hi> the Flood runs until a Weſt and by South-Moon, all the Weſt part of the <hi>Streights-mouth</hi> hath the Flood out of the Weſt, which runs in from Cape <hi>Sprat,</hi> and Cape <hi>Traffalgar</hi> on each ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the ſhore much ſtronger than in the middle to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as far as Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide, and <hi>Apes Hill</hi> on <pb n="248" facs="tcp:104773:130"/> the <hi>Barbary</hi> ſide, and at thoſe two points meets with the Flood, that cometh out of the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, about the point of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> and runs S. W. into the
<hi>Streights</hi> Mouth all the firſt quarter flood, &amp; the remainder of the Tide the flood ſetteth from the Point of <hi>Gibralttar,</hi> Weſt S. W. towards Cape <hi>Cabrita,</hi> at the top of high water there cometh always out of the Weſt between the two Capes a Race of a Current which ſpreadeth the whole <hi>Streights-mouth</hi> from ſide to ſide, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues on neither ſide, ſeldom longer than half an hour; but in the middle of the
<hi>Streights-mouth</hi> the Current runs to Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward very ſtrong all the Tide of Ebb, and the Race of a Current falleth always, between <hi>Apes Hill</hi> and Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> at a Weſt and by South Moon, and at that
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:104773:130"/> inſtant begins the Ebb on the Weſt ſide of thoſe two Points, to run to the Weſtward; The Tide of Ebb on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide runs from Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> about two miles broad from the ſhore as far as the Iſland of <hi>Tariffe,</hi> and runs between the Iſland &amp; the Main. all the Tide of Ebb along by the ſhore towards Cape
<hi>Traffalgar,</hi> but on the South ſide of the Iſland the Ebb runs very narrow except it be in a Set of fair Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Tide of Ebb on the
<hi>Barbary</hi> ſide runs from <hi>Apes Hill,</hi> but narrow along the ſhore as far as the point <hi>Alcaſar,</hi> but on the Weſt ſide of that point thwart of the Bay, the Tide runs about three miles broad, and at Cape <hi>Malabata</hi> which is the Eaſtmoſt point of the Bay of
<hi>Tangier,</hi> about two miles broad, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to the Weſtward out to <pb n="250" facs="tcp:104773:131"/> Cape <hi>Sprat,</hi> and from thence the Ebb runs South Weſt along the ſhore, towards <hi>Sally:</hi> The Ebb to the Eaſtward of Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> &amp; <hi>Apes Hill</hi> is begun by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Race of a Current, which ſpreadeth from one ſide to the other, between <hi>Gibraltar</hi> and <hi>Seuta</hi> Point, and runs in Eaſt North eaſt in the middle, and from the Point of <hi>Apes-Hill</hi> to the Point of
<hi>Seuta</hi> along the ſhore all the firſt half Tide; and the remaining half Tide, the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent runs from Cape <hi>Cabrita,</hi> Eaſt South-eaſt, into the <hi>Streights</hi> by the Point of <hi>Seuta;</hi> and from the Point of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> the firſt half Ebb runs North-Eaſt into the
<hi>Streights</hi> towards Cape <hi>Fangerola,</hi> thwart of Cape
<hi>Trafflagar,</hi> about three miles diſtant from the ſhore lies a Rock 9 foot under water, between which Rock and the <pb n="251" facs="tcp:104773:131"/> Cape, you may ſail through from the Iſland of <hi>Tariffa;</hi> Weſt and by South lies a Ledge of Rocks, 8, 9, and 10 Foot under water, which may be ſeen in foul Weather by the Breach of the Sea. At the Eaſt ſide of the Iſland of
<hi>Tariffa</hi> is a good Rode for a Weſterly Wind, in which you may Anchor between 20 and 13 fathom Water in clear hard ground, but come not to an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor nearer to the Iſland than 13 Fathom, becauſe near the South-eaſt Point of the Iſland is foul ground; the beſt of this Rode is with the South-weſt Point of the Iſland, Weſt South-weſt from you, and the Sand Hill Weſt-North-weſt, and there you ſhall find 14. Fathom water clear ground. Between this Iſland &amp; Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> there is no danger, but what always lies above Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <pb n="252" facs="tcp:104773:132"/> in the middle of this Bay is a Light-Houſe, thwart of which you may Anchor in 12 Fathom Water, clear ground; a fine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the ſhore, one third part of the diſtance from this Light-houſe towards the Cape is 12 Fathom, the ground blew Clay, and that is a good Rode for a North-eaſt Wind, you may borrow on the Cape, the Rocks to the Weſtward of the Cape to 5 Fathom, and on the Eaſt ſide to 7 Fathom, a little to the Weſtward of the Weſtern Point of the Bay of
<hi>Gibraltar,</hi> thwart of a little Valley in the fair way between this Point and Cape <hi>Cabrita</hi> is a Rock 8 Foot under Water, and by the Eaſt ſide of this Rock is 12 Fathom. At the Point of Cape <hi>Malabata</hi> lies a Ledge of Rocks joining to the Land that ſtretcheth a little
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:104773:132"/> way into the Sea, but all above Water, and you ſhall have five fathom water fair by the Rocks: Note the Tide of Ebb runs very ſtrong to the Weſtward by this Point, round the Bay of <hi>Tangier;</hi> To Anchor in the Bay of <hi>Tangier,</hi> in clear ground, bring the Caſtle that ſtands on the North-weſt Corner of the Town, over the North Wall of the Town, and Cape <hi>Malabata</hi> North-eaſt, and there is between 9 &amp; 10 Fathom water at a full Sea.</p>
            <p>To turn through the <hi>Streights</hi> Mouth, the Wind being weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you muſt ply to Windward on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide from the point of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> to Cape <hi>Cabrita,</hi> and from thence to the Iſland of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reffa,</hi> but you muſt turn about the Cape a little before a high Water, that you may have time to make two or three ſhort
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:104773:133"/> Boards to the Weſtward of the Cape before the Race of a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent comes out of the Weſt, which continues but a very little while; which being paſt, the Ebb begins to run to the Weſtward, which runs ſo ſtrong that you may turn up to the Iſland in one Tide of Ebb, (but if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, you may ſtop the Flood any where betweeen the Cape and the Iſland in 12, or 14 Fathom water) and there you muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor until ſo much of the Flood be ſpent, that you may get over to the <hi>Barbary</hi> ſide, to take the firſt of the Ebb there; and if you fall a little to the Weſtward of the Point <hi>Alcaſara,</hi> you may get into the Bay of <hi>Tangier</hi> by a low Water, from whence you may, obſerving the Tide, turn out at pleaſure.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:104773:133"/>
            <head>Theſe BooKs are to be ſold by <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi> at the
<hi>White Hart in Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>CAſſandra,</hi> the fam'd Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, 1667.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Briggs's</hi> Logarithms.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Franciſci Saurez</hi> Metaphyſica.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</head>
               <item>Dr. <hi>John Pell's</hi> Introduction to <hi>Algebra,</hi>
1668.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nich. Mercatoris</hi> Logarithmo-Technia, ſive Methodus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruendi Logarithmos, 1668.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacobi Gregorii</hi> Exercitationes Geometricae,
1668.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Joh. Wallis,</hi> Opera Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, pars 1.
1670.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> pars 2. now in the Preſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baniſter's</hi> Works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hugh Broughton's</hi> Conſent of Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104773:134"/>
                  <hi>Snellii</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Typhis Batavus, <hi>Lugd. Bat.</hi> 1624.</item>
                     <item>Obſervationes Haſſiacae.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Petrus Paaw,</hi> de Oſſibus Amſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reod. 8.
1633.</item>
               <item>A Letter from a Gentleman of the Lord <hi>Howard</hi>'s Retinue to his Friend in <hi>London,</hi> Dated at <hi>Fez,</hi> Nov.
1669.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biblia Hebraea,</hi> Joſephi Athias, 1661.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gualteri Needham,</hi> Diſquiſitio A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomica De Formato Foetu, 1667.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Fortunate Fool,</hi> 1670.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharmacopoeia Londinenſis,</hi> 1668.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Buxtorſius</hi>'s Epitome of his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Grammar, tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>John Davis,</hi>
1658.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crow,</hi> Scriptores in Scripturam. <hi>Now in the Preſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
